<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno V. Jacobi II. Regis. Cap. I. An act of recognition of the just and most undoubted rights of His Majesties imperial crown.</title>
            <title>Laws, etc. (Public general acts)</title>
            <author>Ireland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B24661</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99887637</idno>
  <idno type="VID">190671</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240885334</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing I322E</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide G.6022[122]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R228109</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99887637</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99887637e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B24661)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 190671)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C23:1[122])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno V. Jacobi II. Regis. Cap. I. An act of recognition of the just and most undoubted rights of His Majesties imperial crown.</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc. (Public general acts)</title>
                  <author>Ireland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>56+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Dublin? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Acts passed by the Irish Parliament called by James II after his departure from England.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacking all after p.56 and possibly lacking a general t.p.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Ireland --  History --  War of 1689-1691 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:190671:1"/>
            <head>Anno V. Jacobi II. Regis.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 1. An Act of Recognition of the Just and Most Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Rights of His MAJESTIES Imperial Crown.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Most Gracious Soveraign,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WE Your Majesties most Dutiful and Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects the Lords Spiritual, and Temporal, and Commons in this present Parliament Assembled, most joyfully acknowledging the trancendent mercy of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God in giving your Sacred Majesty a safe and happy Arrival to this your Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in a glorious and peaceable manner, in despight of the Conspiracies and Machinations of Execrable Traytors, and power of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Enemies,<note place="margin">Rebels as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> his Invasion.</note> cannot without Horror consider the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable Defections and Treasons of many of our fellow Subjects, as well in this Realm, as in Your Majesties other Kingdoms; who being desperately wicked, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Impiety by unspeakable Treachery, lately assisted the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> against the Laws of God and Man, unnaturally to invade Your Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and there by odious arts and devices strengthening them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in Power and Faction, by seducing from their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance great numbers of your Majesties Subjects of that Kingdom: First forced your Majestie to withdraw Your Sacred Person from Your Palace of <hi>White-Hall;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">the King in Restraint.</note> and soon after Your Return to the great Ioy of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of Your Loyal Subjects in those parts of <hi>England,</hi> put your Majesty under a guard of Forreigners, compell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing You to go to <hi>Rochester,</hi> where You remained in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint, untill it pleased God of his infinite mercy to your Majesty,<note place="margin">His escape into <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi>
                  </note> and these Kingdoms to give You a happy deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance out of the hands of your Enemies, by escaping in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>France,</hi> from whence your Majesty, to the unexpressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:190671:2"/> Ioy of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll your Loyal Subjects, happily came into this Kingdom.</p>
               <p>And the said Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> having, by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable Assistance of such Traytors and Enemies, fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>otted and Contrived the Ruine and Destruction of this excellent Monarchy, and of all the Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of your Subjects, found it necessary, in order to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e carrying on of his pernicious designs, by aid of the said Traytors, and forreign enemies, to throw down all the bullworks and fences of Law, and to subvert the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and constitutions of Parliaments; that so, at last, he and they might make their way open to the unnatural and perfidious Vsurpation afterward by him and them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished;<note place="margin">the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of preserving the Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> who first professing, by several deceitful Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, that his intent was not to deprive your Majesty of your Imperial Crown, but to preserve the Protestant Religion, and rights of your Subjects by him speciously (but mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t falsly pretended to be subverted). Vnder the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive and unknown name and authority of a Convention of Lords and Commons meeting at <hi>Westminster,</hi> against the Laws of your Majesties Kingdoms, by force and fraud, and an unparalell'd example of Impudence, and Injustice, they took upon them to declare your Royal Throne va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant;<note place="margin">the throne declared vacant</note> and (as if it were their right to dispose the same) of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered your Imperial Crown to the said <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> in such Horrid manner, and Odious circumstances, as is but too well known to the world: which execrable Fact no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can equal, but the barbarous Murder of your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Father of ever blessed and glorious Memory, by a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of wretched men; from whom these late Traytors have borrowed and Revived their desperate Antimonarchie Principles</p>
               <p>And because by this abominable Action a most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>supportable shame and infamy may be imputed to Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of your Majesties Subjects no wise guilty of this Treason. We therefore your Majesties said dutifull and Loyal Subjects the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in Parliament assembled,<note place="margin">abominat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on against the said wicked Acts.</note> being touched with a true sense of our duty, do hereby renounce, Abominate and Protest against that Impious fact, the late Vsurpation of the said <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> and the most unparallel'd Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and Persidiousness of such of your Majesties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, as have by their defections in any sort promoted the same, &amp; all proceedings tending thereunto; And do beseech your Majesty that it may be declared, that the said horrid
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:190671:2"/> Vsurpation and all Acts tending to, and promoting of the same, are against the Law of God, Nature and Nations and have fixt an indelible Infamy on the perjured Heads of such as have been guilty thereof; all,<note place="margin">The Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors had formerly sworn Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity.</note> or most of these Offenders having sworn that it was not lawful to take up <hi>Arms</hi> against your <hi>Majesty</hi> on any pretence whatsoever; and the said <hi>perfidious Criminals</hi> being conscious of their Guilt, and breach of Faith to God, and their Natural Soveraign, after they had manifestly violated the before recited Oath, and also broke the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy,<note place="margin">they abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated their former Oaths, and devised new Oaths to the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surper.</note> have by their own usurpt Authority, taken upon them to Abrogate the said Oaths, and invented new and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Assurances of Fidelity to the Vsurper. We there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your Majesties most Loyal, and most Dutiful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects aforesaid, out of our bounden Duty to God, and your Majesty; and for the vindication of our selves from any Crime that may be imputed to us by reason of the said treasonable Transactions, and the several Rebellions in this Kingdom formed by domestick Traytors in conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the same; and that the world may know the care and duty which oblige us to manifest your Majesties most undoubted Right to your Imperial Crown, and that the same may be transmitted to our posterities, do hereby acknowledge with one full voice of Tongue and Heart,<note place="margin">Recogniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Right of the Crown</note> that your Majesty is our lawful and undoubted Liege, Soveraign Lord and King: And as we cannot make this Recognition too often, or enough; so can there be no way or means so fit as at this time both to sacrifice our unfeigned Thanks to Almighty God for blessing us with a Soveraign adorned with the rarest Gifts of Mind and Body, and upon the knees of our Hearts to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our most constant Faith, Obedience and Loyalty to your Majesty, and next after your Majesty, to his Royal Highness, the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> your most undoubted Son and Heir apparent, our second hope, joy of our Hearts, and Breath of our Nostrils, and your Royal Progeny, in this your High Court of Parliament, where the whole Body of the Realm, and every particular Member there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, either in person, or by representation, upon their own free Elections, are by the Laws of this Realm deemed to be present, do from the bottom of our Hearts yield to the Divine Majesty all humble Thanks and Praises for your Majesties most Gracious, Iust and Merciful Raign over us; and in most humble and lowly manner, do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech your Most Excellent Majesty, that as a further me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:190671:3"/> to all Posterities for ever, to remain amongst the Records of your High Court of Parliament, of our Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence of the before-mentioned inhumane Vsurpation and Treason, and of our Loyalty, Gratitude, Obedience, hearty and humble affection to your Majesty; following herein Authentick Presidents of many former good Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments; It may be published and declared in this High C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urt of Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liament, and Enacted by Authority of the same, that We being bound thereunto by the Laws of God and Man, do Recognize and Acknowledge, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by express our unspeakable Ioys, that immediately upon the Dissolution and Decease of your Royal Brother King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, of ever Blessed Memory, the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Crown of this Realm, and of all other your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Kingdoms and Dominions, did by Inherent Birth-Right, and Lawful and Vndoubted Succession, descend, and come to your Most Excellent Majesty, as being Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neally, Iustly and Lawfully, next and sole Heir of the Blood-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyal of this Realm, as aforesaid: And that by the Goodness of God Almighty, and Lawful Right of Descent under one Imperial Crown, Your Majesty is of this K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngdom, and of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> the most Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent and Mighty King; and thereunto We do most humbly submit, and oblige our Selves, our Heirs and Posterities for ever, until the last drop of our Blood be spilt.</p>
               <p>And we do hereby further declare, that your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Right to your said Imperial Crown,<note place="margin">The Kings Right is from▪ God and not from the People.</note> is originally by Nature, and descent of Blood, from God alone, <hi>by whom Kings Raign,</hi> and not from your People, nor by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue or pretext of any Contract made with them, or any Act of your Estates on that behalf; an Assertion which we Abominate, Detest, and Condemn, as false and tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous; taken up formerly, and since revived by the most odious Parricides that ever lived: And do hereby further publish and declare, that by the undoubted Fundamental Laws of this Kingdom, and of <hi>England,</hi> neither the Peers of this Realm, nor the Commons, nor both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in Parliament, nor out of Parliament, nor the People collectively, or representatively, nor any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons whatsoever ever had, have, or ought to have any Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercive Power over the Persons of the Kings of this Realm; and that our Allegiance to your Majesty, our Natural Liege, Lord and Soveraign, is Indissoluble, and cannot be renounced by Vs, or our Posterities; which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:190671:3"/> Allegiance of us your Subjects is due to your Majesty in your natural Person, from which the Royal Power can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be separated.</p>
               <p>And We do further Recognize and Declare, That within all Your Majesties Realms and Dominions,<note place="margin">The King alone has the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and Militia, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> the Sole and Supreme Power, Government, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and Disposition of the Militia, and of all Forces by Sea and Land, and of all Forts and Places of Strength, is, and by the Laws of this Realm, and of <hi>England,</hi> ever was the undoubted Right of your Majesty, and your Royal Predecessors, Kings and Queens of these Realms. And that both, or either of the Houses of Parliament, or the People Collectively, or representatively, or a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Assembly of Lords Spiritual, Temporal, and Commons, or any of them, on any account whatsoever, cannot, nor ought to pretend to the same, nor can or law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully may raise or levy any War Offensive or Defensive against your Majesty, your Heirs and lawful Successors.</p>
               <p>And for the further abhorring and condemning of such wicked Rebellious Principles that have been distilled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the minds of the people of these your Majesties King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,<note place="margin">Subjects not to be deprived of the King's Protection, nor the King of their ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</note> and to prevent for the future (as much as it is pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible) the contagious venom of such detestable Opinions and Sentiments: We do hereby further Recognize, Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish and Declare, that as it is against the Law of Nature to hinder or deprive your Majesties Subjects of your Royal Protection; so it is directly against the same Law, and the Laws and Statutes of this Realm thereon grounded, to hinder or deprive your Majesty from the service of your Subjects in Peace or War, (being insepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably annexed to, and inherent in your Royal Person) of what perswasion in Religion soever they be, when your Majesty shall have occasion to use the same, whereof your Majesty is the only Iudge; and that it is utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful for your Majesties Subjects of this,<note place="margin">None to resist the King.</note> or any of your Kingdoms, on any pretence whatsoever, actually to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist your Majesty, or our Lawful, Hereditary King for the time being, by Violence, or force of Arms; or to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw their Allegiance from your Majesty, your Heirs and Lawful Successors;<note place="margin">God is the Judge of misusing Authority:</note> but that the Decision in all Cases of a misused Authority by our Lawful, Hereditary King (if any such should happen) must be left to the sole Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, <hi>the King of Kings, and only Ruler of Princes.</hi> All these True and Faithful Declarations of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties undoubted Rights amply set forth in divers Acts
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:190671:4"/> of Parliament of this and precedent Ages, and known to be the fundamental Laws of these your <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> We will for ever support, and maintain against the said Vsur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and his Adherents, and all other Rebels and Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, with the utmost hazard of our Lives and Fortunes which we most humbly beseech your Majesty to adorn with your Royal Assent, without which they cannot be either compleat or perfect, nor remain to Posterity accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our humble desire, as a Memorial of your Princely and Tender Affection towards us, and of our sincere Loyalty and Duty to your Majesty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 2. An Act of Supply for His Majesty for the Support of His Army.</head>
               <p> </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 3. An Act for Liberty of Conscience, And Repealing such Acts or Clauses in any Act of Parliament which are inconsistent with the same.</head>
               <p>VVHereas it is found by experience, that persecut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of People upon the account of Religion, doth no way advance Christian Faith, or Piety, but on the contrary, occasions annimosities and divisions between His Majesties Subjects, and discourages strangers from living amongst them to the great hinderance of the Trade, Peace and Welfare of this Kingdom. And for that our Soveraign Lord the King, hath been graciously pleased, upon several occasions, solemnly to declare his Royal Inclinations, for indulging of tender Consciences, and his constant Resolution of giving free Liberty of Conscience to all his Subjects, to that degree, that there should be no other Test,<note place="margin">Liberty of Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cience to all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing Christiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> or distinction amongst them, but that of Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty. It is therefore Enacted; and be it Enacted by the Kings Most Excellent Majesty, with the Consent and Advice of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this present Parliament Assembled, and by Authority of the same, that all and every person and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons whatsoever professing Christianity, shall have and enjoy Liberty of Conscience, and full and free Exercise of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:190671:4"/> their respective Religions, Ways and forms of Worship; within this Kingdom, without any molestation, loss or penalty whatsoever. And that they and every of them may Meet, and Assemble together, with their Pastors, Teachers, Preachers, Ministers, or other Instructers; to Teach, Preach, and Exercise their several Functions in such Churches, Chapels, private Houses, or other places, as they shall have for that purpose, as to them, and to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them, in their several ways shall seem best and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, so as nothing be taught, preach'd, or done contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to their Allegiance, or contrary to his Majesties peace,<note place="margin">All Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies to be open with freedom of access to all</note> his Crown, and Dignity: And that the said Meetings and Assemblies be always in some open or publick place or places, unto which all persons may have an open, free, and uninterrupted access, and passage; any Act, Statute, Constitution or Ordinance to the Contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
               <p>And be it further Enacted, by the Authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">The Writ <hi>De Heretico Comburendo</hi> all other penalties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> annul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</note> that the Writ <hi>De Heretico Comburendo;</hi> and so much of any Statute, Act, Ordinance, Constitution, or Law, as Directs, Authorizes or Warrants the Issuing, or Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the said Writ, or which inflicts any other Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or Imprisonment, or Forfeiture of Lands, Goods, and Chattels, or the Burning of Pereticks, for or an account of Heresy be, and are hereby Annulled, Repealed, and made Void.</p>
               <p>And be it further Enacted, by the Authority aforesaid;<note place="margin">None obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to take the Oath of Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, nor that of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> cap. 4.</note> that no person or persons shall be hereafter obliged to take the Oath, commonly called the <hi>Oath of Supremacy,</hi> nor the new <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> made or prescribed by a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute made in the third year of King <hi>JAMES</hi> the First His Reign, Chapter the Fourth. And that so much of all, and every Act of Parliament at any time made in this Kingdom, as extends to Oblige, Require, or Provide the tendering, or taking of the said Oaths, or either of them, by any person or persons shall be, and are hereby Repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and made Void; and all Penalties, Forfeitures, and Incapacities; incurred, or to be incurred; for not tendering; or for refusing, or not taking the said Oaths; or either of them, are hereby Discharged and Released.</p>
               <p>And be it further Enacted, by the Authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Repeal of a Clause in the Stat. 14 &amp; 25 <hi>Car.</hi> 2</note> that the Clause in these words following, <hi>(viz.) Other then persons of the Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
                  </hi> inser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in an Act Intituled, <hi>An Act for taking away the Court of Wards, and Liveries, and Tenures in Capite, and by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:190671:5"/> Knights Service,</hi> made in the Fourteenth and Fifteenth Years of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, be, and is hereby Repealed, and made Void; and also the Power by the said Act Granted to the Lord Chancellor of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the time being, and others for the disposing the Custody and Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of Heirs under the age of one and twenty years; of persons dying, not being of the Communion of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and for taking Recognizances, be, and is hereby Repealed, and made Void. And it is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that all the resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of the same Act shall be of the same force and effect; and that all his Majesties Subjects shall have the full be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit thereof as if no part of the said Act had been Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, or no Clause of Restraint or Exception had been in the said Act inserted.</p>
               <p>And also all other Clauses in all and every Acts of Parliament;<note place="margin">General Repeal of all Clauses, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in any Act that may hinder Liberty of Conscience</note> and all Customs, Laws, and Ordinances whatsoever, which are inconsistent with, or repugnant unto this present Act, and the Liberty of Conscience, and free Exercise of Religion hereby intended to be given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all persons professing Christianity, shall be, and are hereby Repealed, Annulled, and made Void.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:190671:5"/>
               <head>CAP. 2. An Act for Repealing the Acts of Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement, and Explanation, Resolution of the Doubts, and all Grants, Patents and Certificates pursuant to them, or any of them.</head>
               <p>WHereas the Roman Catholick Subjects of this Kingdom have for several years, to the apparent hazard of their Lives and Estates,<note place="margin">The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble of the Act.</note> under the Royal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority defended this Kingdom, until at last they were overpowred by the Vsurper <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> in which Quarrel many of them lost their lives, and divers of them (rather than to take any conditions from the said Vsur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per) did transport themselves into foreign parts, where they faithfully served under his late Majesty, and his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Majesty, until his late Majesty was restored to his Crown.</p>
               <p>And whereas the said Vsurper hath seized and seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred all the Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments of the said Roman Catholicks within this Kingdom, upon the account of their Religion and Loyalty, and dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of the same among his Officers, Souldiers, and other his Adherents; and though his Majesties said Roman Catholick Subjects, not only upon the account of the Peace made by his late Majesty in the year <hi>1648.</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so for their eminent Loyalty, and firm adherence to the Royal Cause, might have justly expected to partake of his late Majesties Favour and Bounty upon his happy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storation, which was then extended even to many noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Rebels in other his Countreys and Dominions, which would make amends for the oppression and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice they lay under for many years in the time of the said Vsurper. Yet such were the contrivances set on foot to destroy his Majesty and Catholick Subjects of this Realm, that two Acts of Parliament passed here, the one intituled, <hi>An Act for the better execution of his Majesties Gracious Declaration for the Settlement of his Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and satisfaction of the several Interests of Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers, Souldiers, and other his Subjects there.</hi> The other Act entituled, <hi>For the explaining of some Doubts arising upon an Act entituled, An Act for the better Execution of his Majesties Gracious Declaration for the Settlement of his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:190671:6"/> Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and satisfaction of the several interests of Adventurers, Souldiers, and other his Subjects there;</hi> and for making some alterations of, and additions unto the said Act, for the more speedy and effectual settlement of the said Kingdom, by which many of the said Catholick Subjects were ousted of their ancient Inheritances, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being so much as heard, and the same were distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s Souldiers, and othets, who in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice could not have the least pretention to the same, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the said Peace made in the year <hi>1648,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Iustice, and natural Equity.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is now high time to put an end to the unspeakable sufferings of the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Natives of this Realm (who have eminently manifested their Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to His Majesty against the Vsurper the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>) and to remove the unparallell'd Grievances brought upon them, under colour of the said two Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes; which cannot be otherwise redressed than by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing the said Acts, and restoring the former Proprietors to their Ancient Right. The compassing whereof is much facilitated by his Majesties Royal condescention to apply towards the satisfaction and reprifals of honest Purchasers under the said Acts a great part of the Lands and Tenements forfeited to him by the late Rebellion and Treason committed by Estated persons within this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, who contrary to their Duty and Allegiance to His Majesty, have trayterously joyned with the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Be it therefore Enacted by Your Most Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, with the consent of the Lords Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, and the Commons in this present Parliament As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled, and by the Authority aforesaid: And it is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly Enacted by Authority of the same, that the said two several Acts herein before mentioned, commonly called the <hi>Acts of Settlement,</hi> and Explanation, and the Act of <hi>State,</hi> or Act of <hi>Councel,</hi> commonly called the <hi>Resolution of the Doubts,</hi> by the Lord Lieutenant and Council, upon the Act of Settlement, and explanation thereof, and all and every Clause, Provisoe, Article and Sentence in them, and every of them contained, and all and every Grant, Patent,<note place="margin">The Act of Settlement and Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed.</note> and Certificate, past by vertue of, or under colour or pretence of the said Acts, and Resolutions, or of any or either of them (except what is herein after preserved, or mentioned to be preserved) be, and are hereby absolutely Repealed, Annulled, and made Void, to all intents, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:190671:6"/> and Purposes whatsoever, as if the same had never been made or passed notwithstanding any Misrecital of the Title of them or either of them, or of the Exact time when the said Acts or either of them were made or past.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>II.</hi> And be it further Enacted that all manner of persons who were any way Entituled to any Lands Tenements or Hereditaments, or whose Ancestors were any way Seized, Possessed of, or Intituled to any Lands Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or Hereditaments, in Vse, Possession, Reversion or Remainder, in this Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> on the <hi>22</hi> day of <hi>October 1641,</hi> their Heirs and Assignes, and every person Lawfully Clayming by from or under them, and his and their Feoffeés and Trustees to and for their use or uses, or in Trust for them or any of them, and who were Barred, Excluded, Hindered or Prejudiced by the said Acts, Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions Grants Pattents and Certificates,<note place="margin">All persons Seized the 22d of October 1641 Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored.</note> shall and may have and take such or the like Remedy by Action or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise for Revesting or Recovering the same, as they or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or either of them now might, could, or ought, to have had, or taken in Case the said Acts, and Resolutions or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Grant Pattent or Certificate had never been had, made or past any Clause, Provisoe, Article, Sentence or Restricti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the said Acts, Resolutions, Grants, Pattents, or Certificates, and any limitation, of time, Descent, cast, Common Recovery Iudgment, or Non Clayme, upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Fine or Fines, or upon any other matter or thing, where an Entry or Claime could or would have Aided him or them, or any of his or their Ancestors, Feoffees or Trus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, in any way notwithstanding.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>III.</hi> And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That all Attaind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs and Outlawries, for Treason or any other Offence, and also all Treasons and other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences whatsoever upon account or pretence of the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion mentioned or expressed to have begun or arisen in this Kingdom on the <hi>23d</hi> day of <hi>October 1641,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">All attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders &amp;c up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on account of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion 41. made void.</note> and also all Penalties, Pains, Forfeitures, Barrs, and Disabillities, accrewed or supposed to be accrewed thereby, or by any means or waies touching or relating thereunto, or any way upon account or pretence thereof, be, and are hereby made void Released and Discharged to all Intents and Purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses whatsoever.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>IV.</hi> And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that every Officer and Officers who have the Custody or Keeping of the said Attainders or Outlawries or any of them, or of any the Process, Entries and proceedings
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:190671:7"/> thereof and of all, or any Bookes of Crimination and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations relating thereunto, shall as soon as Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently may be, take the same of the Files and from the Respective Offices,<note place="margin">All At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainders &amp;c to be taken off the File</note> where the same do now Remain, and Cancel the same before or in the presence of all or any the Commissioners of Restitution herein mentioned and any Officer failing to do the same shall Forfeit his Office, and also the summ of <hi>500</hi> pound <hi>sterl.</hi> the Moiety of the said <hi>500</hi> pound to be to your Majesty, and the other Moiety to any person who shall sue for the same by Action of Debt, Bill, Plaint or Information in any of your Majesties Courts of Common Law, in which Action no Essoyne, Protection, or Wager of Law shall be allowed.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>V.</hi> And to the end that every person and persons, and their Heires Executors Administrators and Assignes who hitherto were Barred, Hindered or Delayed from Recovering, Revesting or enjoying his or their just Rights, Titles, or Possessions by any of the matters aforesaid, may with all Convenient speed, be put into and establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his and their said Rights, Titles, and Possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that such three or more persons as by your Majesty your Heires or Successors,<note place="margin">Three or more of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missiioners to hear and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Claymes of persons Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storable</note> by Commission under the great Seal of <hi>Ireland</hi> shall be to that Purpose appointed from time to time shall be Commissioners to hear and determine the Claymes and Titles by English Bill of such person or persons their Heires Executors, Administrators and As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes who are or ought to be Restorable or Entituled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments, by reason of the Repealing or making Void of the said several Acts, Resolutions of Doubts, Grants, Letters, Pattents, Certificates or of any other matter or thing herein before mentioned to be made void Repealed, Released, or Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>VII.</hi> And further that the said Commissioners or any three or more of them shall appoint certain times &amp; places from time to time for their Sitting,<note place="margin">the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners to appoint times for Hearing Claymes.</note> Hearing and Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining the Rights, Titles, and Claimes aforesaid, and shall Issue Summons to the Tenants, and Possessors, of the Lands Claimed before them and for witnesses and upon appearance or in default of appearance then to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed,<note place="margin">To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xamin Titles upon Oath and to award In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions.</note> and Examine the Right and Title of the said Clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant or Claimants upon Oath which Oath they have hereby power to Administer, and take Affidavit in court or
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:190671:7"/> out of Court; &amp; thereupon shall have power to a ward In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juctions for putting into Possession such person or persons as shall appear unto them to be Restorable unto or who ought to be put into Possession of any Lands, Tenements,<note place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners to punish Sheriffs &amp;c. for not Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions &amp;c.</note> or Hereditaments by virtue of this Act, and all Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Prohibitions to be granted to stop or delay the proceedings of the said Commissioners shall be void and of no Effect but all Sheriffs &amp; Coroners to whom any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction or Injunctions for Possession shall be directed, are hereby required and Authorized at their Perils to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute the same, and the said Commissioners are hereby Authorized to Punish all Neglects and Contempts of Sheriffs, Officers or any other person or persons.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>VIII,</hi> And for as much as by reason of the several op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions Distractions and Confusions herein before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned and of the length of time, since the said Ancient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors have been dispossessed as aforesaid the Deeds, Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences and writings of the persons Restorable by this Act, may be either lost or mislaid, so that the same may not spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily or perhaps not at all be had, in Order to make out his or their Tytles, before the Commissioners aforesaid, Be it therefore Enacted that the Iudgments, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree or Sentence of the said Commissoners or of any of them, shall not be Final or Definitive,<note place="margin">The Decree of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners not Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal: in case Deeds can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.</note> but the person or persons and his or their Heires, Executors, Administrators and Assignes, who is or shall be Restorable by vertue of this Act, shall and may at his own will and pleasure use and have his Action and Remedy in any of his Majesties Courts of Law or Equity, for Recovery of his or their Rights, Titles, and Possessions without Resorting to the said Commissioners, or if he be not able to make out his Title before them.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>IX.</hi> Provided always, and be it hereby Enacted and Declared by the Authority aforesaid, That this Act or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing therein Contained shall not Extend nor be Deemed, or Construed to Extend,<note place="margin">Proviso All Fines Conveyan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies Relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses &amp;c. Confirmed▪</note> to annul or make void any Release; Confirmation, Conveyance, Fine, Recovery or Agreement had, made, suffered, or perfected by any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or persons, or their Ancestor or Ancestors, who other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise would have been Restorable by vertue of this Act, But that such Release, Confirmation, Conveyance, Fine, Recovery or Agreement shall be of such like force and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as they would have been, if this Act had never been had or made.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:190671:8"/>
                  <hi>X.</hi> And be it further Enacted by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, that where any person or persons who hath been Transplanted into the Province of <hi>Connaught</hi> or County of <hi>Clare,</hi> or his or their Heires, Assignes, has sold or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed away the Lands or Tenements, there set out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him in Liew of his Ancient Estate and he or his Heires shall notwithstanding such sale of his Transplanted In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest be Restored to his Ancient Estate or hath Released his Right thereto,<note place="margin">A Clause for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naught and County of Clare <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> and the said Transplanted Interest be likewise Restored to the person or persons who was or were Entituled thereto the <hi>22d</hi> day of <hi>October 1641.</hi> or to his or their Heires or Assignes that then the Ancient E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state which shall be so Enjoyed by or Restored to such person or persons who sold the said Transplanted Interest or to his or their Heires, or to any one Clayming by or under him or his Ancestors or to whom he or they Released the same and likewise such other Estate as the said Transplanted person hath or had, or which came from him by descent in Fee to his Heir or Heires shall be, and is hereby made ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able unto and charged with the Lawfull yearly Interest of the purchase money which was paid to the said old Proprietors for the said Transplanted Interest by the person or persons, who bought the same, the said yearly Interest to be paid to your Majesty your Heires and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors after the Expiration of Twenty one dayes next af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Feasts of St. <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>All-saints</hi> yearly by equal portions every year untill the said Original Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase mony be paid unto your Majesty your Heires and Successors in one Entire payment, and the said Purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser of the said Transplanted Estate to be reprized in such manner as herein, after to that Purpose, is expressed and the said Purchase money to be part of the stock of Repriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als And whereas by the Restitution of the Persons here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by intended to be restored to their said Ancient Estates and Proprieties which belonged to them or their Ancestors or to those under whom they Clayme on the <hi>22d</hi> day of <hi>October 1641</hi> divers persons who were Strangers to the several persons to whom some of the said Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Hereditaments were distributed, came into the Possession of the said Lands, Tenements and Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by or under the Purchases or Conveyances after the said Act of Settlement past, and before the first day of <hi>November</hi> last for good and valuable Consideration, and not in Consideration of Blood Affinity or Marriage by or from the Person or
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:190671:8"/> persons to whom the same have been granted or distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, pursuant unto, or under colour of the said several Acts of Parliament, and Resolution of Doubts, or of some or one of them, and whereof Certificate or Patent hath been past since the said first Act of Settlement, and likewise such person and persons whose Ancestors, or themselves, or those under whom they claim, purchased the Estates set forth to transplanted persons in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Connaught,</hi> and County of <hi>Clare</hi> must be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and displaced from their said possessions, and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Estates, and leave the same to the just Owners and Proprietors, thereof, who are to be restored thereto by vertue of this Act. The said persons so to be removed, are hereby intended to be reprized for such their Purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses in manner as herein afterwards is expressed.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>XI.</hi> And whereas a horrid &amp; unnatural Rebellion was lately raised, and still is contrived in this Kingdom, and in other your Majesties Dominions, by great numbers of your Majesties Subjects, and more especially by divers of the persons, and their heirs who had and enjoy'd a great part of the Lands and Tenements which formerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to your Majesties and your Royal Fathers and Brothers Catholick Subjects, and were given out, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stributed by the late Vsurped Powers as a reward for the former Rebellion and Treason herein first mentioned, which said Rebels being not content therewith, but again endeavouring by the like Rebellion and Treason to draw in forreign Forces, and to continue a succession of Vsur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation against your Majesty, and over your most Loyal Catholick Subjects of this Kingdom, in hopes thereby to gain the rest of this Land, as they had obtained a great part of it before, and totally to deprive your Royal Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, and your Heirs and Successors thereof, and of your Crown and Dignity. Divers of the said Rebels went into <hi>England, Scotland, Wales, Holland,</hi> and the <hi>Isles of Man,</hi> and other parts beyond the Seas, to invite and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r most unnatural Enemy the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and your Rebellious Subjects there, to send over Forces into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Kingdom, whilst the rest of the said Rebels in great multitudes arrayed themselves in a rebellious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and seized several of your Majesties Forts, Garrisons and Magazines here for the said Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and your said confederate Rebels, whereby this your Majesties Kingdom was in great danger to be lost; but it pleased Almighty God, by the Courage and Conduct of his Grace
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:190671:9"/>
                  <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> your Majesties Deputy in this Kingdom, with the dutiful assistance of all your Majesties most Loyal Catholick Subjects here, unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mously joyning with your said Deputy, to preserve the same for your Majesty, and to break and defeat the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures and machinations of a great part of the said Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels and Traytors; forasmuch as for the Treasons and Rebellions aforesaid, the said Rebels and Traytors have justly forfeited not only their Estates, Lands and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, but their Lives also.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>XII.</hi> Be it therefore Enacted by your Most Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, by the advice and consent aforesaid, that all and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Manors, Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, Vse, Trust, Possession, Reversion and Remainder, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Redemption, and all and every Estate and Interest whatsoever in Law or Equity within this Kingdom, which on the first day of <hi>August 1688.</hi> or at any time since belonged or appertained to any person or persons whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, who on the said first day of <hi>August 1688.</hi> or at any time since was in Rebellion, or in Arms against your Most Sacred Majesty either in this Kingdom, or in the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> or who corresponded or kept intelligence with, or went contrary to their Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to dwell, or stay amongst the said Rebels, or any of them, or who was or were any way aiding, abetting, or assisting to them, or any of them, be and are hereby for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited unto,<note place="margin">The Estates of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion the first of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust</hi> 1688 vested in his Majesty.</note> and vested in your Majesty, and shall be deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and adjudged to have been forfeited unto, and vested in your Majesty, as from the said first day of <hi>August 1688.</hi> without any Office or inquisition thereof found, or to be found, freed, and absolutely discharged of and from all Estates Tail, and of all remainders and Reversions, to the intent and purpose that the same may be settled, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, granted, and confirmed in such manner as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after is expressed.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <hi>XIII.</hi> (That is to say) that every reprisable person &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,<note place="margin">Persons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved to be reprized</note> his Heirs, Executors, and Administrators, who shall be removed from any of the Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, which are hereby to be restored to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Proprietor thereof, as herein before is expressed, shall be reprized, and have other Lands, Tenements and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditaments of equal value, worth and purchase, set out, and granted unto him out of the said forfeited Lands hereby vested in your Majesty for such Estate or Estates as the Lands from which he or they shall be so removed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:190671:9"/> were held by him at the passing of this Act, And for the more speedy and effectual granting of the said Reprizals.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>XIV.</hi> Be it further Enacted, that if it shall be thought fit or necessary there shall Issue Commissions under the great Seal of this Kingdom,<note place="margin">Commission to Issue and Enquire of the Lands Forfeited</note> to such Commissioners as shall be named by the Lord Chancellor or Lord Keeper of the great Seal of <hi>Ireland</hi> within every of the Cities, Towns and Counties of this Kingdom to inquire and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, what Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Rebells aforesaid were seized, or Possessed off, or intituled unto on the said first day of <hi>Agust 1688,</hi> or at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time since, and the true and real yearly value thereof, and to make return thereof into his Majesties High Court of Chancery with all convenient speed.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <hi>XV.</hi> And be it further Enacted by the Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, that such three or more persons as your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty your Heires and Successors,<note place="margin">Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to be appointed for setting out Repriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als &amp;c.</note> by Commission under the great Seal of <hi>Ireland,</hi> shall from time to time to this purpose appoint, shall be Commissioners for setting forth alloting and distributing the said Reprizals, which said Commissioners or any three or more of them are hereby, Authorized and Impowered, to Receive the Petitions, and Claymes, of such person and persons, who shall demand such Reprizals in which said Petition, and Claym, is to be contained, the quantity and quallity, and the true year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly value of the Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, from which such Petitioner or Claymant was Removed, and the Estate, and Title he had therein, and the Quit-Rents thereout payable, and the said Commissioners, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny three or more of them are to examin the truth thereof, by witnesses upon Oath, and such other Evidences as shall be produced unto them, and upon due Examination thereof, if they finde that such Petitioner or Claymant, or those under whom he Claymed was a Purchaser by Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase made after passing the said first Act of Settlement,<note place="margin">Purchasors upon valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration Reprized.</note> and for good and valuable Consideration before the first of <hi>November</hi> last and not for or in consideration of Blood Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity or Marriage from by or under the person or persons, to whom the Estate so Claymed was granted or distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and whereof Certificate or Pattent was past since the said first Act as aforesaid, or that the said Petitioner or Claymant, or those under whom he Claymes was or is a Purchaser for valuable considerations of any Transplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Intrest in the Province of <hi>Connaught</hi> or County of <hi>Clare,</hi> then to set forth unto such Petitioner or Claymant,<note place="margin">Purchaser of a Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizable.</note>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:190671:10"/> other Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments of equal va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, worth, and purchase, and for the like Estate as the said Petitioner or Claymant had in the Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or Hereditaments from which he was or shall be Removed as aforesaid, And the said Commissioners or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny three or more of them, are hereby Required and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized to grant their Certificates under their hands and seals to the said Petitioner and Claymant expressing the Denominations,<note place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners Certificate of the Lands gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize a good Warrant to the said Chancellor <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> Quantity, Quality, and Number of Acres of the said Lands so alloted, and the Barony and County wherein the same do lye, and the Estate thereof to be granted, and the Rent thereout to be Reserved upon produceing of which Certificate, the Lord Chancellor or Lord Keeper of the great Seal of <hi>Ireland</hi> is hereby Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized and Impowred without any further Warrant to cause effectual Letters Pattents to be made and past to the said Claymant of the Lands so certified to be Alloted unto him, and under the Rents and for such Estate and Estates as in the said Certificate shall be to that purpose Expressed,</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <note place="margin">A Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted person be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized to make out his purchase mony.</note>
                  <hi>XVI.</hi> Provided always and be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that such person or persons as shall Claym or Demand Reprizals for any Transplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Estate or Interest, shall before he or they have any Reprizal or Reprizals for the same Allotted or set out to them, make full and true Discovery and proofe of the whole Original purchase mony which was paid for the said Transplanted Estate by the first Purchaser thereof, to the person or persons or his Heires to whom the said Estate was Originaly set forth or allotted, by way of Transplantation.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <hi>XVII.</hi> And the said Commissioners upon due Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and proof of the said Purchase mony are to certifie the Quantity thereof,<note place="margin">the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners to certifie the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase mony</note> and the Estate of the Ancient Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor which is to stand charged with the yearly Interest thereof into your Majesties Court of Exchequer, to the end that the same may be Levyed as it shall grow due from time to time, untill the Original Purchase mony be paid in one entire payment to your Majesty your Heires and Successors, the said Principal and Interest to be paid to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Reprizals as aforesaid.<note place="margin">a penalty upon such Transplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted persons that do not m ke out their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase mony</note>
               </p>
               <p n="18">
                  <hi>XVIII.</hi> And be it further hereby Enacted, that in case at any time hereafter, it shall be discovered that any person or persons, claiming Reprizals for any such transplanted Interest, hath not discovered the full purchase Money first
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:190671:10"/> paid, for the said transplanted Estate, but hath concealed any part thereof, then, and in such case, the person or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons who hath so concealed any part of the said purchase Money, shall forfeit double the summ so concealed, or not discovered; the one moiety of which forfeiture shall be to your Majesty, your Heirs and Successors; and the other moiety to such person or persons as shall sue for the same, by Bill, Plaint, or Information wherein no Essoyn, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection or Wager of Law shall be allowed.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <hi>XIX.</hi> Provided also, and be it further Enacted,<note place="margin">No Estate restorable to old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors vested in his M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>jesty</note> that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Act, nor any thing therein contained shall be deemed or construed, to vest in your Majesty, your Heirs or Successors any the Lands, Tenements, Hereditaments, or Chattels Real, Right, Title, Service, Chiefry, Vse, Trust, Condition, Fee, Rent-Charge, Mortgage, Right of Redemption, of Mortgages, Recognizance, Iudgment, Extent, Right of Action, Right of Entry, Statute, or any other Estate, of what nature or kind soever, which are hereby restorable, according to the true intent and meaning of this Act to any ancient Proprietor, or his Heirs or Assigns, and the which have been vested, or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, or supposed to have been vested in your Majesties said Royal Father and Brother, or in either of them, by vertue of both, or either of the said Acts of Settlement, and Explanatory Act, or Resolutions of Doubts, or by vertue of any of the said Attainders, or Outlawries, which are herein before Repealed and made void, or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to be Repealed or made void, but that all and every person and persons, whose Titles, or whose Ancestors Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, were hitherto thereby barred, forfeited, or any way prejudiced or interrupted, shall and may be restored there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, according to their ancient Rights and Titles, as herein before to that purpose is expressed or intended.</p>
               <p n="20">
                  <hi>XX.</hi> Provided always, and be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">No remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctant upon any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Estate vested in his Majesty</note> that nothing in this present Act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained shall any way extend, or be construed to extend, to forfeit to, or vest in his Majesty, his Heirs or Successors, any Remainder or Remainders, Reversion or Reversions for valuable consideration, limited or settled by any Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement or Conveyance, made for such valuable conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration either of Marriage and Marriage Portion, or other valuable consideration, whatsoever, upon any Estate for life, or lives, to any person or persons, who have not, or shall not aid, abett, or assist any person or persons in the Vsurpation or Rebellion aforesaid; such Remainder or
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:190671:11"/> Remainders,<note place="margin">discover the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase mony</note> Reversion or Reversions as are limited by any Conveyance wherein there is any power for revoking or altering all or any use or uses therein limited, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so such Remainder and Remainders, Reversion and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versions as are limited upon any Settlement or Convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of any Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Plantation Lands, and all Lands, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements and Hereditaments, held or enjoyed under such Grants from the Crown, or Grants upon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission or Commissions of Grace, for remedy of defective Titles in the Raign of King <hi>James</hi> the First, or King <hi>Charles</hi> the First; in which several Grants respectively, there are Provisoes or Covenants for raising or keeping any number of Men and Arms for the King's Majesty against Rebels and Enemies, or for raising of men for his Majesties Service for expedition of War, always ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted and fore-prized; all which emainders and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versions, limited by such Conveyances, wherein there is a power of Revocation, for so much of the Lands, Vses and Estates therein limited, as the said power doth or shall extend unto, and all such Remainders, as are deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved or limited of Plantation Lands, or other Lands held as aforesaid, under such Grants made by the Crown, shall by authority of this present Parliament be deemed, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strued, and adjudged void, debarred, and discharged, to all intents and purposes whatsoever, against his Majesty, his Heirs and Successors, and his or their Grantees, or As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signees; and the said Lands, Tenements and Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments belonging to such Rebels as aforesaid, shall be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted in his Majesty, his Heirs and Successors, freed and discharged of the said Remainder and Remainders, and every of them; and to the end the Reversions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders saved and preserved by this Act, may appear with all convenient speed.</p>
               <p n="21">
                  <hi>XXI.</hi> Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that the respective persons entituled to such Remainders,<note place="margin">Persons en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled to any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder, to exhibit their claims in 60 days.</note> do within sixty days next after the first sitting of the Commissioners for executing this Act, exhibit their Claims before the said Commissioners, and make out their Title to such Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder or Remainders, so as to procure their Adjudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Certificate for the same, or the Adjudication and Certificate of fome three or more of them; and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that all Remainders, for which such Adjudications and Certificates shall not be procured, at or before one hundred and twenty days, after the first sitting of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:190671:11"/> said Commissioners shall be void, and for ever barred and excluded. Any thing in this Act or other matters to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding. Nor shall this Act extend to vest in your Majesty, or barr any Remainder limited to <hi>Dudley Bagnell</hi> Esq; upon the particular E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state of <hi>Nicholas Bagnell</hi> of <hi>Newry</hi> Esq; in <hi>Newry,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bagnell's Provisoes.</note> the Lordships and Lands of <hi>Mourne,</hi> and all other Manours and Lands now or lately belonging to the said <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Bagnell</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland;</hi> Provided the same be such a Remainder as was not, or is not in the power of the said <hi>Nicholas Bagnell</hi> to barr. And forasmuch as We, your Majesties most Loyal and Dutiful Subjects, always have been, and for ever intend to be more studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and industrious to secure and advance your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Revenue, than to lessen or diminish the same.</p>
               <p n="22">
                  <hi>XXII.</hi> And wheras the Quit-Rents, or Kings Rent reserved, or now payable unto your Majesty, your Heirs and Successors, would determine by Repealing the said Acts, if some provision were not made to continue the same.</p>
               <p n="23">
                  <hi>XXIII.</hi> Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">A Clause concerning Quit-Rents</note> that all Lands and Tenements, which by the said Acts of Settlement, and Explanation, were charged with, or made liable to Quit-Rent▪ shall be, and hereby are charged with, and made liable to the same, or the like Quit-Rents, to be paid to your Majesty, your Heirs and Successors, as in and by the said Act of Settlement and Explanation were appointed and directed. Saving and excepting the Quit-Rents due and payable out of the Earl of <hi>Antrim</hi>'s E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state, which were Granted to the late Earl of St. <hi>Albans.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Saving the Earl of <hi>Antrim</hi>'s Estate, and other Quit-Rents granted by Letter Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> And saving and excepting all such Lands and Tenements whereof the Quit-Rents have been by Letters Patents under the Broad Seal of <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> Granted, or Released to the ancient Proprietor, or Proprietors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or to some other person or persons in trust for them, or reduced in the hands of the ancient or new Proprietors, since the Act of Settlement, and Explanation, by reason of barren or unprofitable Ground; whether such reduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was by Patent under the Broad Seal, or Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, or other Order of Commissioners, having power to reduce the same, which Lands &amp; Tenements, are for the future to be charged only with such Quit-Rents, or Crown-Rents, as are by such Letters-Patents, Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficates, and Orders, respectively reserved and specified. And further, that all Lands, which immediately before
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:190671:12"/> the passing of this present Act were not liable to any Quit-Rents, and shall be, by, or pursuant to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Act,<note place="margin">Reprisals.</note> restored to the ancient Proprietors thereof. And likewise all Lands within this Kingdom, which being vested in your Majesty by this present Act, or by, or upon account of the present Rebellion, or of any Treason com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by any person since the first day of <hi>August</hi> last, shall be distributed, or given out for Reprizals by the Commissioners for executing this Act, or otherwise Granted by your Majesty, your Heirs or Successors, to any person or persons, Bodies Politick or Corporate, shall be,<note place="margin">Bodies Politick made liable to Quit-Rents.</note> and are hereby charged with, and made liable to the same, or the like Quit-Rents to be paid to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, your Heirs and Successors, as in and by the said Act of Settlement, and Explanation, were appointed or directed to be paid out of any other Lands in the respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Provinces where such Lands do respectively lye: So that the Rent formerly reserved to the Crown on such Lands, exceed not the Rent hereby reserved; but where the Rents formerly reserved, do exceed the Rent hereby to be reserved, the said former Rents only shall be paid.</p>
               <p n="24">
                  <hi>XXIV.</hi> And be it further Enacted by the Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid,<note place="margin">All arrears of Quit-Rents re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served to his Majesty.</note> that all Arrears of the said Quit-Rents reser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the said former Acts, which were due to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty on the first day of <hi>May 1689.</hi> shall be answered, and duly paid to your Majesty; and that your Majesty shall and may recover, and levy the same in such manner, and by all such ways and means as you might have done, if this present Act had never been made, Any thing in this Act contained to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
               <p n="25">
                  <hi>XXV.</hi> And in regard the Measne Profits of the said ancient Estates which are hereby restorable, are to be discharged, as hereafter expressed.</p>
               <p n="26">
                  <hi>XXVI.</hi> Be it further Enacted by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said,<note place="margin">No Debts before the 23th of <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tober,</hi> 1641. discharged,</note> that all interest of Money for any Debt or Debts contracted before the <hi>23th</hi> day of <hi>October 1641.</hi> and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Estate of any person restorable by this Act, may be chargable, be, and are hereby discharged, and released, for such time as the person or persons who should have paid the said Debts, were barr'd, and kept out of their Estates by the said Acts, or Rebellion; but the original Debts are not to be discharged by this Act.</p>
               <p n="27">
                  <note place="margin">No mesne profits but from the time of an Entry made</note>
                  <hi>XXVII.</hi> And be it further Enacted by the Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, that no person restorable by vertue of this Act, shall sue for, or Recover any measne profits of the Estate
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:190671:12"/> so Restorable, but only for such Mesne Profits as shall accrew or grow due after his demanding Possession or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencing Suite for the Lands so Restorable after the passing of this Act.</p>
               <p n="28">
                  <hi>XXVIII.</hi> And be it further Enacted by the Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, that the Estate or Estates, to be set out or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted to any person or persons, by way of Reprizals,<note place="margin">Lands set out for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizals Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Judgment <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> by vertue of this Act, or any other Estate which he or his Heires shall have, shall be Lyable and Subject to all such Iudgments, Statutes and Recognizances for payment of mony, Rent Charges, Annuities, Mortgages, Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and all other Estates, Vses, Trusts, Limitations, Settlements, Charges and Incumbrances of the persons so reprized, or removed in such manner as the Estate from which he shall be so removed, would be Lyable in case he never were removed from the same: But in case any person hereby removable to make room for an old Propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etor be a Forfeiting person, or is not Intituled to have Reprizals then and in such case it is hereby Declared and Enacted that all and every person and persons who before the seaventh day of <hi>May 1689,</hi> had any such Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance as before Expressed or any Iudgment at any time before the <hi>22</hi> day of <hi>May 1689:</hi> on the said Estate hereby Restorable to the old Proprietor shall and may have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizals for the same out of the Common Stock of Repriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, at the rate of ten years purchase.<note place="margin">Incumbran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces not to Exceed the Estate which was Lyable thereunto</note>
               </p>
               <p n="29">
                  <hi>XXIX.</hi> Provided always that such Incumbrances or the Reprizals to be had or Allotted for the same, shall not exceed the value of the Estate which was Lyable thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and which is restorable to the old Proprietor thereof, or to his Heires or Assignes.</p>
               <p n="30">
                  <hi>XXX.</hi> And be it further hereby Enacted, that where any old Proprietor or his Heires,<note place="margin">Transplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Estates made Lyable for the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors debts.</note> who had or held any new Estate by Transplantation or otherwise by or under the said Acts hereby Repealed or any of them shall by vertue of this present Act be removed from the same, that then and in such case the Ancient Estate to which old Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors or their Heires shall be restored, and likwise all such o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Estate which such Ancient Proprietor or his Heires by descent in Feé under him, shall have, shall be, and is hereby made Assets for the Ancestors Debts, and Lya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make satisfaction for all such Iudgments, Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizances and Statutes for payment of mony and also for all Rent Charges, Annuities, Mortgages and all other Estates, Vses, Trusts, Limitations and Settlements,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:190671:13"/> Charges and Incumbrances of the said old Proprietor and his Heires in such manner as the said new Estate from which he or they shall be so Removed, would have been Lyable in Case he or they were never removed from the same Except the Leases made by such persons who are to be restored to the Lands, they or any of them were Seized or Possessed of.</p>
               <p n="31">
                  <hi>XXXI.</hi> And furthermore for prevention of the great Inconveniencies which may happen by the sudden remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of Lesseés Farmers or under Tenants from the Lands Tenements or Hereditaments, whereof they are now in Actual Possession, and which are hereby to be Restored to the Ancient Proprietors thereof their Heires or As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes.</p>
               <p n="32">
                  <note place="margin">Leases made good</note>
                  <hi>XXXII.</hi> Be it further Enacted by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, that all such Leases in writing of the said Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments hereby Restorable, and which were made before the first day of <hi>May 1688.</hi> meérly in Consideration of Rents Duties or other valuable year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Reservations. And not in consideration of any Fine or Incomb, or of Blood, or Affinity: And by virtue whereof the Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments thereby demised are at this time enjoyed and held by the present Ter-te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants and Occupiers thereof, be and are hereby made good and confirmed to the said Ter-tenents and Occupiers for and during so much of the Term or time in such Lease and Leases limitted and expressed as shall not Exceéd the number of twenty one years or threé lives yet to come and unexpired and for all the Lands,<note place="margin">The mansi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on house Excepted</note> Tenements and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditaments thereby demised. Except that Messuage or Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement which in the year <hi>1641;</hi> was the Mansion House of the old Proprietor or his Assignes. And except also De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>measnes thereunto belonging, that is to say, the Town and Lands whereon the said Mansion-House then stood and the said Tenant or Lesseé and his Executors Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrators and Assignes for the Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, so by them to be held and detained by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of such Lease or Leases are to pay the yearly Rent and Duties thereout Reserved or their just Proportion thereof to the said Ancient Proprietor hereby Restorable and to his Heires and Assignes and to give him and them Copies or Counterparts of the said Lease or Leases,<note place="margin">The rent Reserved payable to the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors.</note> and their own Obligations for performance thereof or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise to accept of a new Lease for the Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Hereditaments, so to be enjoyed, and under the like Rent, Proportionably, and for such time or Term as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:190671:13"/> shall be then Vnexpired of the said former Demise.</p>
               <p n="33">
                  <hi>XXXIII.</hi> And whereas in some Cases the Lease or Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, which such Lesseé or Lesseés had, might have beén ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beneficial Leases for a greater Term, and Originally made in Consideration of Fines by them, given to their Lessors for the same, or in Respect of Improvments, and as it is unequitable on the one side, that such Lesseés should lose their Fines, Bargains and Improvements, without satisfaction for the same, so it is on the other side unreasonable that the Old Proprietor who hath beén hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto kept out of his Estate, and is hereby barred from the Measne Profits thereof, should be obliged to bear the loss and damage of Leases so made at an under Rent and low value.</p>
               <p n="34">
                  <hi>XXXIV.</hi> Be it therefore Enacted by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, that the said Lessor,<note place="margin">A clause Concerning his Majes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Leases made when Duke of <hi>York</hi>
                  </note> his Heires or Assigns who is to be Reprized for the said Lands, shall out of the Lands which shall be to him granted by way of Reprizal, make and perfect unto the said Lesseé, his Executors, Administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors or Assigns, a Lease of Lands of the like value, and for such Term or time of the said former Lease, as will be unexpired at the Removal of the said Lessor, and that the said new Lease shall be under the like Rents, Reservati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Covenants and Conditions as in the said former Lease were expressed, but in case the said Lessor be a Forfeiting person and not Reprizable by this Act, then the said Les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seé and Lesseés, shall be Reprized for their said Leases, out of the Common stock of Reprizals according to the Methods herein before set forth, but such Leases in Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session; and not now in any Forfeiting person as were made by your Majesty of the Lands held by your Majes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty under the Title of the said Acts are to stand good and effectual at the Election of the Lesseés, their Executors, Administrators and Assigns, and the Rent and Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion thereof,<note place="margin">Keating Lease re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served.</note> to devolve and come to the Old Propietor thereof, and particularly one Lease bearing date the first day of <hi>April 1675.</hi> made by your Majesty unto <hi>John Keating</hi> Esq; for the Term of twenty six years to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence from the first day of <hi>May</hi> then next ensuing the date thereof, of the Town and Lands of <hi>Blackrath</hi> in the County of <hi>Kildare,</hi> under the yearly Rent of Eighty one pounds fifteén shillings <hi>sterl.</hi> shall in like manner stand good and effectual, Notwithstanding any sale made by your Majesty unto him the said <hi>John,</hi> of the Inheritance of the said Lands, or any Merger of the said Lease, but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:190671:14"/> the Reversion and Rent of the said Lands so leased is hereby to come to the Old Proprietor thereof, his Heirs and Assigns.</p>
               <p n="35">
                  <hi>XXXV.</hi> Provided always, and be it Enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid, that all and every person and persons who is or are at the time of passing this Act, Seized or Possessed of any Houses, Messuages, Manors, Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments within this Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and who are by vertue of this Act, or any Clause therein contained, to be removed from the Seizin or Posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion thereof, or of any part thereof, shall have such Reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and competent time given, and allowed him or them, for the Removal of themselves, their Families and stocks, as the Commissioners for Execution of this Act,<note place="margin">A clause for underte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants.</note> or any threé of them, shall think fit, and appoint, not exceéding one year from the first day of <hi>May 1689,</hi> and the same to be under such competent Rent, as the said Commissioners shall think fit to be paid to the person and persons, his, and their Heirs, Executors and Administrators, who is, or are by this Act Restorable to the said Houses, Messuages, Manors, Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, any thing in this Act, or any other matter or thing to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary thereof, in any wise Notwithstanding.</p>
               <p n="36">
                  <hi>XXXVI.</hi> Provided also, and be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that all and every person and persons who sow any Corn or Rootes in any Lands,<note place="margin">A clause for the Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of Lessees to be Remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</note> Tenements and Hereditaments, whereof they or any of them, are now at the the time of the passing of this Act, Seized or Posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, shall have, perceive, and take the full benefit and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage thereof, and have freé Liberty of Ingress, Egress and Regress for the making up and preserving, and of Carrying away and disposing of the said Corn and Roots, or any part thereof, as he or they shall think fit, he or they Paying and Allowing for the same to such person and persons as shall be Restored to the said Lands so Sown with Corn and Roots, according to the Custome of the Country.</p>
               <p n="37">
                  <hi>XXXVII.</hi> And whereas there are divers Poor and distressed Widdows and Relicts whose Deceased Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands,<note place="margin">A clause for widdows.</note> had they beén a live, would have beén Restorable by this Act, and be thereby enabled to leave some Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to their said Widdows and Relicts, but in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard their said deceased Husbands, by means of the seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Acts, and other matters herein before Expressed and Repealed, were kept from having any Seizin or Posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:190671:14"/> of the Estates, which should of Right be enjoyed by them; and for want of such Seizin, the said Widows and Relicts are not by the Common Law of this Land inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled to any Dower, and therefore are in danger of perish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p n="38">
                  <hi>XXXVIII.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Want of Seizin no Barr.</note> Be it therefore Enacted by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, that the want of such Seizin shall be no barr or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to the Widows and Relicts aforesaid, but that every Widow and Relict, whose Husband, if living, would, or might be restorable by this Act, shall, and may have and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover such Dower, or proportion of her said Husbands E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state, as she might recover by the Common Law, if her said Husband had a Seizin in Deed, or in Law thereof. And the Commissioners for restitution herein before appointed, or to be appointed, are required to cause the same to be set forth, and allotted; or the said Widows and Relicts, may, if they think fit, use, and have their remedies at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, and if <hi>Neunque</hi> seize <hi>que</hi> Dower, or any such Plea shall be pleaded against any of them, it shall be suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for every such Widow and Relict, to give in Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that the Estate which her Husband should have had, and was kept out of by any of the Acts or matters here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Repealed, was such whereof she might recover Dower, in case he were actually seized, according to the Estate to him limited; and upon proving thereof, every such Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and Relict shall recover, as well as if her said Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band had been actually seized of the said Estate; but such Widows and Relicts as had or enjoyed any Ioyntures to them limited, shall only have the benefit of such Ioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p n="39">
                  <hi>XXXIX.</hi> Provided always, and be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that all and every the Honors,<note place="margin">The Lord <hi>Kingston</hi>'s Estate ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted in his Majesty.</note> Manors, Lands, Tenements, Remainder and Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, whereof <hi>Robert</hi> Lord Baron of <hi>Kingston</hi> now is, or at any time heretofore has been lawfully and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully seized or possessed of in his Demesne, as of Fee, or Fee-tail, to, or of any other Estate of Inheritance in right of his Ancestors (that is to say) of <hi>John</hi> late Lord Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Kingston,</hi> or the Lady <hi>Catherine</hi> his Wife, situate, lying and being in the Counties of <hi>Cork</hi> and <hi>Roscommon,</hi> or elsewhere within this Kingdom; and which hath been settled upon, or limited to the said <hi>John</hi> Lord Baron of <hi>Kingston,</hi> by his Father, or Grandfather, Sir <hi>John,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert King,</hi> or by any of them, or to the said <hi>John</hi> Lord Baron of <hi>Kingston,</hi> and the Lady <hi>Catharine</hi> his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:190671:15"/> Wife, or to either of them, by Sir <hi>William Fenton,</hi> Kt. and Dame Margaret his Wife, or to either of them, and whereof the said Sir <hi>John,</hi> or Sir <hi>Robert,</hi> or the said Sir <hi>William Fenton</hi> were seized or possessed of respectively on the <hi>22th</hi> day of <hi>October 1641.</hi> with all the Rights, Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, or Interest, which they, or any of them respectively had thereunto, be and are hereby vested, and settled in his Majesty, and his Heirs, to be disposed of as his Majesty shall think fit, subject nevertheless to such legal and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Incumbrances, as the same would have been liable unto, in case this Act had never past, any thing herein contained to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
               <p n="38">
                  <hi>XXXVIII.</hi> Provided always, and be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">A Clause concerning the Lands of <hi>Chapel-Izard.</hi>
                  </note> that the Capital Messuage, Town and Land of <hi>Chapel-Izard,</hi> alias <hi>Izad,</hi> with all other the Appurtenances thereunto belonging, and every part and parcel, now at the passing of this Act, occupied, possessed, and enjoyed as part or parcel thereof, and the Capital Messuage of the <hi>Phenix,</hi> and all the Houses, Messuages, Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments within the King's Park, adjoyning unto, or near this City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> in as large, free, and ample a manner as the same is now at the passing of this Act, possessed, and enjoyed by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, or any person claiming by, from, or under his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, shall be, and are hereby vested in the King's Majesty, his Heirs and Successors, and shall be held and enjoyed by his Majesty, his Heirs and Successors, any thing in this present Act, or any other matter or thing whatsoever to the contrary, in any wise notwithstanding. And in case any ancient Proprietor, or Proprietors thereof, hath, or or have not been already satisfied for his or their Interest therein, that then such ancient Proprietor or Proprietors shall be Reprized according to his Title and Interest in the said Lands, out of the forfeited Lands, according to the Rules of this Act.</p>
               <p n="39">
                  <hi>XXXIX.</hi> Provided always, and be it Enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforesaid,<note place="margin">The Port Corn pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served to the Lord Chief Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> that the Lord Chief Iustice of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Court of Kings-Bench, the Lord Chief Baron of his Majesties Court of Exchequer, and the Master of the Rolls, or any other of his Majesties Officers of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for the time being, shall and may have and receive such Port Corn of the several Rectories which have been formerly paid, and received, any thing in this present Act, or any other matter or thing whatsoever to the contrary thereof, in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
               <p n="40">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:190671:15"/>
                  <hi>XL.</hi> And whereas in pursuance of an Agreement made and concluded between <hi>Richard</hi> late Earl of <hi>Clanriccard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Proviso concerning the Earls of <hi>Clanriccard</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>Charles</hi> Lord Viscount <hi>Muskery,</hi> and <hi>Margaret</hi> Vice-countess <hi>Muskery</hi> his Wife, Heir General to <hi>Ulick</hi> late Lord Marquess of <hi>Clanriccard,</hi> several provisions have been made and Enacted in the said Acts of Settlement, and Explanation for settling the Estate of the Family of <hi>Clanriccard;</hi> since which time several Deeds, Conveyan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Settlements Provisions, Writings, Decree, Award and Agreements of and concerning the Honours, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the said Family, or whereof <hi>William</hi> late Earl of <hi>Clanriccard</hi> was seized or possessed, were made and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by the said <hi>William</hi> late Earl of <hi>Clanriccard,</hi> or by his Children after his Decease, or with their consent, which are not intended to be weakned, or avoided by this Act.</p>
               <p n="41">
                  <hi>XLI.</hi> Be it therefore Enacted by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, that the said several Deeds, Conveyances, Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Provisions, Writings, Decree, Award, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greements, according to the several and respective Estates, Vses, Trusts, Remainders, Limitations and Provisions therein mentioned, shall be, and remain firm and valid in Law, according to the said Award lately made between the Family of <hi>Clanriccard,</hi> and the Limitations and Vses therein set forth; and that the several Deeds, Conveyan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Settlements, Provisions, Writings, Decree and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, to the Vses and Limitations in the said Award be of the same force and vertue, and in the same plight and condition to all intents and purposes, as if this present Act had never been made against the Heir General of <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> late Lord Marquess of <hi>Clanrickard, Richard</hi> late Earl of <hi>Clanrickard,</hi> and all persoms claiming by, from, or under them, their Ancestors, or any, or either of them, any thing in these presents to the contrary notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, saving the Right, Title, and Interest of all Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chasers and Strangers, their Heirs, Executors, Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrators and Assigns.</p>
               <p n="42">
                  <hi>XLII.</hi> And whereas the Right Honourable <hi>Hellen</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tess of <hi>Clanriccard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Lady <hi>Clanric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cards</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viso</note> having heretofore had her Dower of the Estate of her deceased Husband <hi>John Fitz Gerald</hi> Esq; set out unto her; in which Dower several parcels of Lands were comprized, that did belong in <hi>October 1641.</hi> to old Proprietors, Restorable by this Act.</p>
               <p n="43">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:190671:16"/>
                  <hi>XLIII.</hi> It is hereby Enacted, that the said Countess shall be Reprized out of the other two Thirds of the said Estate late in the Seisin of <hi>Edward Villiers</hi> Esq; and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharine</hi> his Wife, in Lands of equal value, worth and purchase, that shall be forfeited to his Majesty, for, and during the life of the said Countess, to supply what shall be <hi>Bona Fide</hi> Evicted from her by any such Old Propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etor.</p>
               <p n="44">
                  <hi>XLIV.</hi> And whereas by a particular Proviso in the Act commonly intituled,<note place="margin">The Lord <hi>Carling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fodr</hi>'s Proviso.</note>
                  <hi>An Act for the better Execution of His Majesties Gracious Declaration for the Settlement of this Kingdom of</hi> Ireland, <hi>and satisfaction of the several Interests of Adventurers, Souldiers, and other his Subjects there:</hi> It is amongst other things Enacted, That <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bald</hi> late Earl of <hi>Carlingford</hi> shall have, hold, possess, and enjoy to him and his Heirs, all those the Lands, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, Tenements and Hereditaments in the County of <hi>Lowth;</hi> whereof the said <hi>Theobald</hi> Earl of <hi>Carlingford,</hi> upon the first day of <hi>August</hi> in the year <hi>1661.</hi> was posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, or were sett out, assigned, or granted to the said <hi>Theobald</hi> by way of <hi>Custodium,</hi> or otherwise, in order to a further Settlement thereof, to, and on the said <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bald,</hi> Earl of <hi>Carlingford,</hi> and his Heirs, for, and in liew of the Estate of <hi>Colooney</hi> in the County of <hi>Sligoe,</hi> and also that the said <hi>Theobald</hi> Earl of <hi>Carlingford</hi> shall have and enjoy to him and his Heirs, the Manors, Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, whereof <hi>Christopher Taaffe</hi> of <hi>Braganstowne,</hi> and <hi>Theophilus Taaffe</hi> of <hi>Cookes-town,</hi> or either of them, or any of their Ancestors, or any other Person or Persons, to their Vse, or in Trust for them, or any of them, stood Seized, or possessed, upon the <hi>22th</hi> of <hi>October 1641.</hi> And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the said Manor, Lands, Tenements and Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taments are by this present Act to be restored to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Proprietors thereof, or unto their Heirs or Assigns, and also several other Lands Granted unto the said <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bald</hi> Earl of <hi>Carlingford,</hi> and his Heirs, lying and being in the Counties of <hi>Meath, Sligoe,</hi> and <hi>Tipperary,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>Nicholas</hi> now Earl of <hi>Carlingford</hi> will be a great Sufferer, if not otherwise provided for by this Act.</p>
               <p n="45">
                  <hi>XLV.</hi> Be it therefore Enacted, &amp; it is hereby further En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the Authority aforesaid, that the Commissioners for Execution of this Act, shall forthwith set out in Repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zals other Manors, Lands, Tenements &amp; Hereditaments Forfeited unto, or vested in his Majesty by vertue of this
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:190671:16"/> Act, or upon the account of any attainder of Treason of Equal value Worth and Purchase with the Manors, Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, from which the said <hi>Nicholas</hi> Earl of <hi>Carlingford</hi> or his Heires are to be Removed or Dispossessed by vertue of this present Act, and which were held by the said <hi>Nicholas</hi> Earl of <hi>Carlingford</hi> by vertue of the said Acts of Settlement and Explanation, or of either of them, or by Pattent or Pattents upon the said Acts all and singular which Lands and Premisses so set out in Reprizals, the said <hi>Nicholas</hi> Earl of <hi>Carlingford</hi> shall hold to him and his Heires at and under the same or like Tenures, Rents and Services as all Purchasers are to hold by this Act the Reprizals set out to them or any of them and Subject to such Mortgages, Charges and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrances as the Lands from whence he or they are to be Removed were and are at the time of the passing of this Act any thing in this present Act or any other matter or thing to the Contrary thereof in any wise Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
               <p n="46">
                  <hi>XLVI.</hi> Provided alwayes and be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Lord <hi>Gall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi>'s Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viso.</note> that this Act or any thing herein Contained shall not be Construed or Expounded in any Courts either in Law or Equity to vest in the Kings most Excellent Majesty his Heires or Successors, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise barr any Remainder or Remainders, or any other Right Title or Interest whatsoever that ought to have descended or come, or which shall or may hereafter descend or come upon or to <hi>Frances Lane</hi> now wife to <hi>Ulick</hi> Lord <hi>Viscount Galway</hi> by vertue of any Deéd, Will or other writing whatsoever made and Executed by <hi>George</hi> Lord <hi>Viscount Lanesborough</hi> deceased, and that all the Right, Title and Interest whatsoever in respect of the premisses be saved to the said <hi>Ulick</hi> Lord <hi>Viscount Galway,</hi> and Dame <hi>Frances</hi> his wife this Act or any thing herein Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to the Contrary in any wise Notwithstanding Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes excepted such Lands, Tenements and Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as were at any time withheld or detayned from the Ancient Proprietor or Proprietors on account of any Title derived or pretended to be derived from or under the said Acts of Settlement and Explanation or either of them and not under the Proprietor or his Heires.</p>
               <p n="47">
                  <hi>XLVII.</hi> And whereas by a particular Proviso in the Act Commonly Intituled an Act for the better Execution of his Majesties gracious Declaration for the Settlement of this Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the satisfaction of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:190671:17"/> Interests of Adventurers Soldiers and other his Subjects there it is amongst other things Enacted that the Town of <hi>Mullingare</hi> in the County of <hi>Westmeath</hi> with all the Houses,<note place="margin">Lord For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes Proviso</note> Castles, Tenements Lands &amp; Commons there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto belonging, and Forfeited to his late Majesty <hi>Charles</hi> the Second of happy Memory should be and were by the said Act settled upon the Earl of <hi>Granard</hi> and his Heires by the name of Sr. <hi>Arthur Forbes</hi> Baronet according to a grant thereof passed to him by Letters Pattents under his said late Majesties great Seal of <hi>Ireland</hi> bearing date the <hi>27th</hi> day of <hi>July</hi> in the <hi>13th</hi> year of his said late Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Raign.</p>
               <p n="48">
                  <hi>XLVIII.</hi> And whereas the said Earl of <hi>Granard</hi> hath in Consideration of a Considerable Marriage Portion setled the said Town of <hi>Mullingare</hi> with all and singular the premisses on <hi>Arthur</hi> now Lord <hi>Forbes</hi> Eldest Son of the said Earl of <hi>Granard,</hi> and whereas the said Town of of <hi>Mullingare</hi> and all other the premisses, with their and every of their appurtenances are by this present Act to be Restored to the Ancient Proprietors thereof or unto their Heires or Assignes whereby the said <hi>Arthur</hi> Lord <hi>Forbes</hi> will be agreat Sufferer if not otherwise Provided for by this Act.</p>
               <p n="49">
                  <hi>XLIX.</hi> Be it therefore Enacted and it is hereby further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for the Execution of this Act shall forthwith set out in Reprizals, other Manors, Lands, Tenements and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments Forfeited unto or vested in his Majesty by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this Act or upon account of any attainder of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of equal Value Worth and Purchase with the said Town of <hi>Mullingare</hi> and other the said Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Hereditaments, from which the said <hi>Arthur</hi> Lord <hi>Forbes</hi> or his Heires are to be Removed or disposses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by vertue of this present Act or any Clause or matter therein Contained all &amp; singular which Lands &amp; Premisses so set out in Reprizals the said <hi>Arthur</hi> Lord <hi>Forbes</hi> shall hold to him and his Heires at and under the same or like Tenures, Rents and Services as all Purchasers are to hold by this Act the Reprizals set out to them or any of them, any thing in this present Act, or other matter or thing to the Contrary thereof in any wise Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
               <p n="50">
                  <note place="margin">A Proviso for Francis Plowden Esq;</note>
                  <hi>L.</hi> Be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that whereas <hi>Francis Plowden</hi> Esq; is, and for several years past has been seized in Fee of several Houses, Back-sides,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:190671:17"/> Waste-plots and Gardens, lying and being in the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and Town of <hi>Gallway,</hi> by and under the last Will and Testament of Dame <hi>Catharine Plowden</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lict of Sir <hi>Daniel Treswell</hi> Kt. deceased; He the said <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Plowden</hi> having paid above two thousand pounds <hi>sterl.</hi> in Debts and Legacies, out of the said demised Premisses, pursuant to the said Will, that the Commissioners for executing this Act, shall forthwith sett out, and allow in Reprizal unto the said <hi>Francis Plowden,</hi> his Heirs and As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs, to his and their use, Lands, Tenements and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments, of equal value, worth and purchase, with the said several houses, waste-plots and gardens, from which the said <hi>Francis Plowden,</hi> his Heirs or Assignes is, or are to be removed, for restoring the Ancient Proprietors, by this Act, any thing herein contained to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
               <p n="51">
                  <hi>LI.</hi> Provided always,<note place="margin">A Proviso for <hi>John Browne,</hi> Esq;</note> that <hi>John Browne</hi> Esq; and his Heirs and Assigns shall in trust for his Creditors, and for support of his Iron-works, which are of publick advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to your Majesty, and this Kingdom, have, hold, and enjoy all and every the Furnaces, Store-houses, Mills, Dwelling Houses, and Gardens, and other Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments built, or made by him, or on his account, in the County of <hi>Mayo,</hi> for his own, his Clerks, and Workmens Dwellings and Conveniences to attend the said Works; as also all Damms built by the said <hi>John Browne,</hi> for sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the said Works, with power for Repairs, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore usually done; and next the said Works, and most contiguous to them, so much of the Lands, which by the Rules of this Act would be taken away from the said <hi>John Browne,</hi> or his Assigns, and restored to the ancient Proprietors, as is, or shall be necessary for the Gardens, Dwelling Houses, and Grazing of the Cattel and Horses of the several Clerks, Workmen and Labourers employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or to be employed by the said <hi>John Browne</hi> about the said Works; and the Commissioners for execution of this Act, are hereby impowred to ascertain the quantity and rates of the said Lands that shall be necessary for the said <hi>John Browne,</hi> his Clerks, Dwellers, Workmen and Labourers to be employed about the said Works respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, as aforesaid, and to order and appoint such Rents to be paid yearly to the ancient Proprietors, and their Heirs, by the said <hi>John Browne,</hi> and his Heirs, out of the said Lands, as they shall think fit, regard first being only had to the intrinsical value of the said Lands.</p>
               <p n="52">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:190671:18"/>
                  <hi>LII.</hi> And whereas <hi>Martin Supple</hi> Esq; having been resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as an Innocent by the Commissioners for execution of the said Act of Settlement,<note place="margin">A Proviso for <hi>Martyn Supple</hi> Esq;</note> to the ancient Estate of his Ancestors, in the Lands and Tenements of <hi>Ighermur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowmore, Ightermurrowbegg, Ballinistbudning, Nockglass, Ballinemiznagh,</hi> and other Lands in the Barony of <hi>Imo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kelly,</hi> and County of <hi>Cork;</hi> after which Restitution, Suit or Contest being Commenced, or moved by <hi>Roger</hi> late Earl of <hi>Orrery,</hi> who pretended a Title to the said Lands, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the late Vsurped Powers. And whereas the said <hi>Martin Supple</hi> being not able to withstand the Power of the said Earl, was necessitated to purchase his Peace and Quiet, by conveying, or exchanging his said ancient E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state unto the said Earl, and to accept for the same the Lands of <hi>Dummadimore, Drummadibeg, Farnahelly, Buoghallane</hi> in the said Barony &amp; County; which Lands were held by the said Earl, under the Title of the said Acts of Settlement, and Explanation, or of one of them, and therefore by this present Act are restorable to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Proprietors thereof.</p>
               <p n="53">
                  <hi>LIII.</hi> Be it therefore Enacted by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, that all Conveyances &amp; Assurances made by the said <hi>Martin Supple</hi> to the said <hi>Earl,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Supple</hi>'s Proviso.</note> of the said ancient Estate, or of any part thereof, be, and are hereby annulled, and made void, to all intents and purposes whatsoever; and that the said <hi>Martin Supple</hi> be, and is hereby restored to the said ancient Estate, and shall and may hold and enjoy the same, according to such Estate and Title as he had therein before the said Conveyance or Exchange thereof, made, and subject, and liable unto all Remainders, Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, Vses, Trusts, Limitations, and all other Estates, Charges and Incumbrances as the said Estate or Lands from which the said <hi>Martyn Supple</hi> is to be removed, were, or ought to have been liable unto, any thing herein to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
               <p n="54">
                  <note place="margin">Collonel <hi>Butler</hi>'s Proviso.</note>
                  <hi>LIV.</hi> Provided always, and be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that this Act, or any thing therein contained, shall not be construed or adjudged to vest in your Majesty, or to barr any Remainder or Remainders limited to Collonel <hi>Richard Butler,</hi> or to any of his Sons, upon the respective particular Estates limited to <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>Ormonde,</hi> and his Brother, in, and of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Estate, which on the one and twentieth day of <hi>October 1641</hi> did rightfully belong unto <hi>James</hi> late <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Ormond</hi> deceased, or the Lady Dutchess his Wife, and the same
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:190671:18"/> to be subject to all Incumbrances, whereunto the same ought to be liable, in case this Act were never made.</p>
               <p n="55">
                  <hi>LV.</hi> Provided alwayes that the Remainder so limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the said <hi>Collonel Richard Butler</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Butler</note> and his Sons be such as is not or was not in the power of the said <hi>Iames</hi> now <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Ormond</hi> and of his said Brother or of either of them to Bar.</p>
               <p n="56">
                  <hi>LVI.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">London Derrys Proviso.</note> And be it further Enacted by the Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, and it is hereby Declared to be the true Intent and Meaning of this Act, that all Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, Vse, Trust, Possession, Reversion or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder, Chattel Real and all and every other Estate, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Law or Equity, of what nature or kind soever within this Kingdom, which on the said first day of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust 1688,</hi> or at any time since did belong or appertain to the Society, Governors and Assistance <hi>London,</hi> of the new plantation of <hi>Ulster</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or to any other body politick or Corporate deriving under them, or Composed, or Consisting of any of the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> by whatsoever name or names, the same or any of them are called, be and are hereby vested in your Majesty, your Heires and Successors as from the first day of <hi>August 1688,</hi> and to be part of the Stock of Reprizals herein before mentioned, saveing always, the Right, Title, Estate and Interest, of the Corporation of the Mayor Commons and Citizens of <hi>Londondery,</hi> and <hi>Colerean.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="57">
                  <hi>LVII.</hi> And whereas several waste Plots of ground,<note place="margin">A Clause concerning wast grounds on which Goals <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are built.</note> within several <hi>Cities, Towns, Burroughs</hi> or the <hi>Suburbs</hi> thereof, within this Kingdom, at the publick Charge of the several Freéholders, and Inhabitants of the several Respective <hi>Counties, Cities, Towns</hi> and <hi>Burroughs,</hi> have beén Purchased from the then Proprietors, or Reputed Proprietors thereof, and great Summs of Mony layd out and expended by them, in Building of Session-Houses, Goals, houses of Correction, and other publick Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies thereunto belonging, upon the said Waste Plots of ground, for the publick good, and advantage of this Kingdom, And whereas the said waste Plots of ground or some of them so purchased and Improved upon, may by this present Act to the great prejudice of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth be Restored unto the old Proprietor thereof, if not by some special Clause or Proviso prevented.<note place="margin">Proprietors not to be Restored to such Lands but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized</note>
               </p>
               <p n="58">
                  <hi>LVIII.</hi> Be it therefore Enacted by the Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, and it is hereby Enacted that all the Lands Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements and Hereditaments so Purchased as aforesaid,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:190671:19"/> and whereupon any Session Houses, Goales, Houses of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection are built, shall be, and are hereby vested in your Majesty your Heires and Successors to the use herein af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Expressed, and that the several and Respective old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors of the said waste Plots of ground shall by the Commissioners for Execution of this Act, be forthwith Reprized for the same out of some of the Forfeited Lands vested in your Majesty your Heires &amp; Successors by vertue of this Act, of Equal Value worth and Purchase, with the said waste Plots of ground before any building or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements made thereupon, To have and to hold the said Lands to be set out in Reprizals to them, and every of them their Heirs and Assigns at and under the same or like Tenures, Rents and Services as all Purchasers are to hold by this Act, the Reprizals set out to them, or any of them, any thing in this present Act, or any other matter or thing to the Contrary thereof in any wise Notwithstanding.</p>
               <p n="58">
                  <hi>LVIII.</hi> Provided alwayes, and it is hereby Declared that such of the said waste Plots so built upon,<note place="margin">A Clause concerning Goals ctc. built upon Cons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ground</note> as did not formerly belong unto, and was the Consecrated ground or scite Circuit, and Ambit of any Monastery, Abby or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Religious House, shall be and Remain vested in your Majesty your Heires and Sucessors to the said publick Vses, for which the same were so Purchased and built upon, and as to all such of the said waste Plots so built upon as did formerly belong to, and was the Consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ground or scite Circuit and Ambit of any Monastery, Abby or other Religious House, the same shall Be and Remain vested in your Majesty your Heires and Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors to be disposed of, to such Pious or Charitable Vses, as your Majesty your Heires &amp; Successors shall think fit.</p>
               <p n="59">
                  <hi>LIX.</hi> And, Whereas some meriting persons who are to lose Considerable Estates by this Act, might by the foregoing Rules be intituled to small or no Reprizals, but by their Eminent services, may in a special manner me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Your Majesties Grace and Favour.</p>
               <p n="60">
                  <hi>LX.</hi> Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that your Majesty may in such special Cases set forth and grant Reprizals to such meriting persons, or by your Majesties Letters under your Majesties privy Signet or Sign manuel, order the Commissioners for Executing this Act, to set forth Reprizals for them, And likewise if your Majesty shall so think fit, to appoint and ascertain where and what Lands shall be set out to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:190671:19"/>
               <head>CAP. 5. An Act for taking off all Incapacities on the Natives of this Kingdom.</head>
               <p>WHereas by several Acts of Parliament, and Acts of State, or Acts of Council heretofore made, and past in this Kingdom, and by several Grants, and Letters Patents of Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and Imployments, and by divers Deeds, Gifts, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vises, Wills, Testaments and Leases, divers Prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Conditions, Covenants and Provisions, were, and are ordained and devised to disable and incapacitate some of the Natives of this Kingdom, in respect of being of Irish Blood, or for some other mark of distinction from other your Majesties Subjects here from receiving, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chasing, having, holding, or enjoying Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments, Offices or Employments in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>And whereas the said Acts, and the Prohibitions, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, Covenants, and Provisions aforesaid, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacities, Disabilities and Distinctions thereby devised and ordained, have been, and are of very great disadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and prejudice to your Majesties Subjects here; and have occasioned, and daily do occasion much dis-union and division betwixt them, to the weakning of this Nation.</p>
               <p>Be it therefore Enacted by the King's Most Excellent Majesty,<note place="margin">All Incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities taken off.</note> with the Advice and Consent of the Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Temporal, and Commons in this present Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Assembled; and by the Authority of the same, That all and every the ancient Natives of this Realm, of Irish Blood, shall be, and are hereby made capable of all manner of Employments within this Realm, and of purchasing Lands in Plantation Countreys, and else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; and to have and receive the same by descent, or purchase, as any other of the Subjects of this Land, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of English Blood: And that all Clauses, Provisions, Conditions and Restrictions in any Patents, Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, Grants, Deeds, Gifts, Devises, Wills, Leases, Statutes, Laws, or otherwise, that do put any Incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities on any natural born Subject of this Realm, either of Irish Blood, or otherwise, by reason of his Name, Blood, or Religion, be, and are hereby Repealed, Annul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:190671:20"/> and made utterly void; and all Forfeitures on such account are hereby Released, and Remitted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 6. An Act to Continue two Acts made to prevent Delays in Execution, and to prevent Arrests of Judgments, and Superseding Executions.</head>
               <p>VVHhereas an Act of Parliament past in this Realm in a Parliament held at <hi>Dublin</hi> the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteenth and eighteenth years of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, Entituled, <hi>An Act to prevent delays in extending Statutes, Judgments, and Recognizances;</hi> and another Act Entituled, <hi>An Act to prevent Arrests of Judgments, and Superseding Executions;</hi> both which Acts were to continue for the space of three years, and to the end of the then next Session of Parliament. And whereas the said Acts by experience are found to have been of great advantage.</p>
               <p>It is Enacted, and be it hereby Enacted by the King's Most Excellent Majesty,<note place="margin">The two Acts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued.</note> by and with the Advice and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this present Parliament Assembled, and by the Authority of the same, That the said several Acts of Parliament, and all the Clauses, Sentences and Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles in them, and each of them contained, shall for ever hereafter endure and remain in full Force and Vertue in Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 7. An Act for taking away the Benefit of Clergy in certain Cases of Felony for two years.</head>
               <p> </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 8. An Act for Repealing a Statute Intituled, An Act for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision of Ministers in Cities and Corporate Towns, and making the Church of St. <hi>Andrews</hi> in the Suburbs of the City of <hi>Dublin</hi> Presentative for ever.</head>
               <p>WHereas by an Act of Parliament made in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteenth and eighteenth years of the Reign of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:190671:20"/> our late Dread Soveraign Lord <hi>Charles</hi> the Second of famous Memory, Entituled, <hi>An Act for Provision of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters in Cities and Corporate Towns, and making the Church of St. <hi>Andrews</hi> in the Suburbs of the City of <hi>Dublin</hi> presentative for ever,</hi> It is ordained, that it shall &amp; may be lawful for the Lord Lieutenant, or other Chief Governor or Governors, and six or more of his late Majesties Privy Council of this Kingdom, to allot, ascertain, set forth, and charge any summ or summs of Money to be paid unto the several and respective Incumbents, and their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective Successors within the City and Suburbs of <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> and Liberties thereunto adjoyning; and other Cities and Towns Corporate of this Kingdom, who have actual Cure of souls in each Parish respectively, out of each house and houses belonging to the said Parish, whether it be by apportioning the said Money and Payment according to the yearly value of each House, or otherwise, so as the same Payment do not exceed twelve pence <hi>sterl.</hi> for every pound of the yearly value of each House; such yearly value always to be intended, as the same shall be valued upon Oath by persons to be nominated in that behalf, and authorized by Commission under the Great Seal of this Kingdom, by direction of the Lord Lieutenant, or other Chief Governor or Governors for the time being, of this Kingdom, such Commission to be Returned under the Hands and Seals of the Commissioners to the Clerk of the Council for the time being; and that after such Allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment so made, and Summe or Summs of Money ascer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, charged, and set forth to be paid as aforesaid, and approved by the Lord Lieutenant, or other Governor, or Governors and Council of this Kingdom, such charge on such Inhabitant of each House, shall be as good and effectual in law, as if the very same summe or summs which shall be so charged, had been particularly expressed, and incerted, to be paid out of each House; and that the said Summe so allotted, or charged upon each Inhabitant, should be received by the Church-Wardens respectively, and by them paid to the several and respective Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bents, and their Successors, by four portions every year by the Inhabitant, or respective Inhabitants thereof, with power of distraining for the fame, as by the said Act more at large appeareth.</p>
               <p>And whereas the Duties and Payments aforesaid ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be a new Imposition, and are become very grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous and oppressive to the Inhabitants of Cities and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:190671:21"/> Towns Corporate within this Kingdom, Be it therefore Enacted by the Kings most Excellent Majesty, by and with the Advice and Consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal and Commons in this present Parliament as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled, and by the Authority of the same, that so much of the said Act as extends to the Granting, Imposing or Securing the duties or payments of twelve pence in the pound as aforesaid, be and is hereby Repealed and that the Residue of the said Act relating to the making of the said Church of St. <hi>Andrew</hi> Presentative for ever, and provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Building thereof, and for Purchasing Lands and Livings for the use of the said Church, shall remain in full Force.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 9. An Act for Repealing the Act for keeping and Celebrating the 23d of <hi>October</hi> as an <hi>Anniversary</hi> Thanks-giving in this Kingdom.</head>
               <p>VVHereas the keeping and Celebrating the Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty third of <hi>October</hi> as an Anniversary Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving in this Kingdom according to the Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made in the fourteenth and fiifteenth yeares of King <hi>Charles</hi> the second, is the occasion of great strife, Quarels, and Annimosities between his Majesties Subjects of this Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Be it therefore Enacted by the Kings most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice &amp; assent of the Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual &amp; Temporal and Commons in this present Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment assembled, and by the Authority of the same, that the said Act of Parliament made in the said fourteenth and fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth yeares of <hi>Charles</hi> the second for Keeping and Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating the said Twenty third day of <hi>October</hi> as an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversary Thanksgiving in this Kingdom, be and is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Repealed and made Void.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:190671:21"/>
               <head>CAP. 10. An Act Declaring that the Parliaments of <hi>England</hi> cannot binde <hi>Ireland,</hi> and against Writs of <hi>Error</hi> and Appeals, to be brought for Removing Judgments, Decrees and Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces given in <hi>Ireland</hi> into <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHereas this his Majesties Realm of <hi>Ireland</hi> is and hath been always a distinct Kingdom from that of his Majesties Realm of <hi>England,</hi> always Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by his Majesty and his Predecessors according to the Ancient Customs, Laws and Statutes thereof, and as the People of this Kingdom, did never send Members to any Parliament ever held in <hi>England,</hi> but had their Laws continually made and Established by their own Parliaments, so no Acts passed in any Parliament held in <hi>England,</hi> were ever binding here, excepting such of them as by Acts of Parliament passed in this K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngdom, were made into Laws here, yet of late times and especially in the times of distractions some have pretended that Acts of Parliament passed in <hi>England</hi> mentioning <hi>Ireland</hi> were binding in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as these late opinions are against Iustice and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Equity,<note place="margin">Statutes in <hi>England</hi> do not bind <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </note> so they tend to the great oppression of the people here, and to the overthrow of the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Constitutions of this Realm: And to the end that by these modern and late opinions no person may be further deluded;</p>
               <p>Be it therefore Enacted by the Kings most Excellent Majesty, by the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this present Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament assembled, and by Authority of the same, and it is so hereby declared, that no Act of Parliament past, or to be past in the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> tho <hi>Ireland</hi> should be therein mentioned, can be, or shall be any way binding in <hi>Ireland,</hi> excepting such Acts past, or to be past in <hi>England,</hi> as are, or shall be made into Law by the Parliament of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whereas several Writs of Error, were formerly sued out and Returnable into the Kings Bench in <hi>England</hi> in order to Reverse Iudgments given in his Majesties Court of Kings Bench in <hi>Ireland;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Writs of Error from <hi>England</hi> Barred</note> And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as most of the said Writs of Error have been brought for delay, and thereby many of his Mae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ities Subjects of this
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:190671:22"/> Realm were greatly hindred from recovering their just Rights, and put to vast Charges in attending such Suits in <hi>England;</hi> for the prevention whereof, Be it hereby En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the Authority aforesaid, that no Writ of Error shall be hereafter brought out of <hi>England</hi> in order to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move any Record, or Transcript of Record out of his Majesties Court of Kings-Bench in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or out of any other Court of Record here, into <hi>England,</hi> in order to Reverse any such Iudgments.</p>
               <p>But in regard Iudgments to be given in his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Court of Kings Bench in <hi>Ireland</hi> may happen some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to be erroneous;<note place="margin">Errors to be redres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the Exchequer Chamber.</note> Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that where any Iudgment shall at any time hereafter be given in the said Court of Kings-Bench in <hi>Ireland</hi> in any Suit or Action of Debt, Detinue, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Accompt, Action upon the Case, <hi>Ejectione Firmae,</hi> or Trespass, first Commenced, or to be first Commenced there, other than where the King's Majesty shall be Partie, the Plaintiff, or Defendant, or other person or persons against whom any such Iudgment shall be given, may at his Election su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> forth of the High Court of Chancery in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> a special Writ of Error to be Devised in the said Court of Chancery directed to the Chief Iustice of the said Court of Kings-Bench in <hi>Ireland</hi> for the time being, Commanding him to cause the said Record, and all things concerning the said Iudgments to be brought before the Iustices of the Common-Pleas, and the Barons of the Exchequer here into the Exchequer Chamber in <hi>Ireland,</hi> there to be Examined by the said Iustices of the Common-Pleas, and the Barons of the Exchequer; which said Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices of the Common-Pleas, and Barons of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, or any four, or more of them, by vertue of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Act, shall thereupon have full Power and Authority to Examine all such Errors as shall be assigned or found in or upon any such Iudgment as the Law shall require, other than for Errors to be assigned, or found for, or concerning the Iurisdiction of the said Court of Kings-Bench in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or for any want of form in any Writ, Return Plaint, Bill, Declaration, or other Pleadings, Process, Verdict, or Proceeding whatsoever, and other than for such Mistakes, Errors, or Failings, as are now supplyed,<note place="margin">One Judge or Baron may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the Court.</note> or helped by some Statute or Statutes in force within this Realm.</p>
               <p>And that any one or more of the said Iustices and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons in the absence of the rest, shall have Power to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:190671:22"/> the said Court, and continue the Proceedings of the said Writ of Error from time to time; and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the said Iudgment shall be Affirmed,<note place="margin">Record to be reman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and Judgment to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> or Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; the said Record, and all things concerning the same shall be Removed, and brought back into the said Court of Kings-Bench, that such further Proceedings may be thereupon, as well for Execution as otherwise, as shall appertain.</p>
               <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,<note place="margin">Further re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy in Parliament</note> that such Reversal, or Affirmation of any such former Iudgment shall not be so final, but that the Party who findeth himself grieved therewith, shall and may sue in the High Court of Parliament in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the further and due Examination of the said Iudgment, any thing herein to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
               <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that from the end of this present Session of Parliament no Execution shall be stayed in the said Court of Kings-Bench, by Writ of Error, or Supersedeas thereupon,<note place="margin">No Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion stayed without Bail in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> after Verdict and Iudgment thereupon in any Action personal whatsoever, unless a Recognizance with Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, according the Statute made in the tenth year of the Raign of our late Soveraign Lord King <hi>Charles</hi> the First, shall be first acknowledged in the said Court of Kings-Bench.</p>
               <p>And further,<note place="margin">Bail in Eje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionae fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae.</note> that in Writs of Error to be brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Iudgment after Verdict in any Action of <hi>Ejectione Firmae,</hi> no Execution shall be thereupon, or thereby stayed, unless the Plaintiff or Plaintiffs in such Writs of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, shall be bound unto the Defendant in such Action of <hi>Ejectione Firmae</hi> in such reasonable Summe as the said Court of Kings-Bench shall think fit, with condition, that if the Iudgment shall be affirmed in the said Writ of Error; or that the said Writ of Error be discontinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in default of the Plaintiff or Plaintiffs therein, or that the Plaintiff or Plaintiffs be Non-suited in such Writs of Error, that then the said Plaintiff or Plaintiffs shall pay such Costs Damages, summe and summs of Money as shall be Awarded upon, or after such Iudgment affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Discontinuance, or Non-suit had: And to the end that the same summe and summs, and damages may be ascer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; Be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that the said Court of <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> upon such affirmation, discontinuance or Non-suit, shall issue a Writ to Inquire as well of the Measne profits, as of the Damages by any
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:190671:23"/> waste committed after the first Iudgment in <hi>Ejectione Firmae;</hi> and upon the Return thereof Iudgment shall be given, and Execution awarded for such Measne Profits, and damages and also for the Costs of Suit.</p>
               <p>And whereas of late times several persons have brought Appeals before the House of Lords in <hi>England,</hi> in Order to Reverse Decrees granted in the High Court of Chancery in <hi>Ireland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Appeals to the house of Lords or Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates <hi>&amp;c.</hi> shall be void.</note> which tend to the great charge, trouble and vexation of such of his Majesties Subjects as have obtain'd such decrees, and is an apparent new En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachment upon the fundamental Constitutions of this Realm, and also Appeals before Delegats in <hi>England:</hi> Be it therefore Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that no person or persons whatsoever, do hereafter presume to sue out any such Appeals, or to tender, or produce any such Appeal to the Lord Chancellor, or Lord Keeper of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or to any of the Officers of the said Court of Chancery, and that such Appeals shall be void, and that no Appeal whatsoever to Reverse any Decree or Sentence past, or to be past in <hi>Ireland,</hi> shall be brought into <hi>England,</hi> either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the House of Lords there, or any Commissioners or Delegats of Appeal, and that all such Appeals shall be disallowed.</p>
               <p>And for rendering this present Act the more Effectual; Be it hereby Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that it shall be a High Misdemeanor in any person or persons whatsoever, that shall in drawing of Pleadings either in Law or Equity,<note place="margin">Penalty for Offending this Act.</note> or in any Bill of Exception to be Filed in any Court in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or that at any Tryal before any Court within this Realm, shall deliberatly Insist that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Act of Parliament made or to be made in <hi>England,</hi> wherein <hi>Ireland</hi> is or shall be mentioned, is or can be bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Ireland,</hi> though it should not be made into a Law here by any Act made, or to be made, in a Parliament held or to be held here; And also that it shall be a High misdemea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nor in any person or persons whatsoever, who within this Realm shall tender or produce any Writ or Writs of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror out of <hi>England</hi> in his Majesties Court of Kings Bench in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or to all or any the Iudges of the said Court for the time being, Returnable to the Court of Kings Bench in <hi>England,</hi> or that shall tender or produce any Appeal to the Lord Chancellor, or Lord Keeper, of <hi>Ireland</hi> for the time being, or to any of the Officers of the said Court of Chancery, or to the Chancellor, Treasurer and Barons of the Exchequer from the House of Lords
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:190671:23"/> in <hi>England,</hi> or that shall tender any Appeal out of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to any Spiritual Iudge or Spiritual Court, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legats within this Realm, in Order to Reverse any sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence given in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by any court of Delegats in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> And that if any person or persons shall Offend herein, he shall be Fined and Imprisoned according the Discretion of the court where he shall be prosecuted for the same.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 11. An Act for adnulling and making Void all Pattents of Offices for life or during good behaviour.</head>
               <p>WHereas several Offices within this Realm, were passed in Pattent to several Grantees during the life or lives of one or more persons, or during good beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, by which many of them were Encouraged to mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>use their Authorities, and that many of the said Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were granted in Reversion to others, by Letters Pattents, and Even grants made in Reversion, upon Reversions of such Offices which hath beén, and is like to be the occasions that many Offices requiring skill, and knowledg, are and will be Executed by unskilfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, to the great prejudice of many of his Majesties Subjects;</p>
               <p>And whereas several of the said Offices rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to his Majesties Revenue are past in Pattent to some who having not skill or knowledg to Execute the same, his Majesty is obliged to Imploy others to Act therein, and allow them a yearly allowance to the great Diminution of his Majesties Revenue, And for that seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the said Officers have with drawn themselves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, who being Commanded to repair hither refused or omitted to come; for temedy whereof.<note place="margin">Grants in reversion made void.</note> Be it E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacted, and it is hereby Enacted by his most Excellent Majesty, by the Advice and Consent of the Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Temporal and Commons in this present Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and by Authority of the same that all Pattents past in Reversion or Reversions of any Office or Offices of what kind soever, within this Kingdom, shall be and are hereby declared to be Null and Void;<note place="margin">Grants for Life or du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring good behaviour made void.</note> and of no Effect whatsoever; And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that all Pattents whereby any Office or Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:190671:24"/> whatsoever within this Kingdom, were granted for life or lives, or during good behaviour, shall be and are hereby <hi>ipso facto</hi> void to all intents and purposes whatsoever, and that all such Pattents are and shall be void, from the 20th day of <hi>May</hi> in the year of Our Lord God 1689, without any Suit, Action or Process to be prosecuted for avoiding the same.</p>
               <p>Provided that nothing in this Act contained, shall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend or be construed to extend to any Office or Offices heretofore granted to any person or persons whatsoever,<note place="margin">Saving for Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> by any Charter or Charters heretofore passed for erecting of any Corporation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 12. An Act for the Punishment of persons who bring in the Counterfeit Coyn of Foreign Realms, being Currant in this Realm, or Counterfeit the same within this Realm, or <hi>wash, Clip, File,</hi> or <hi>Lighten</hi> the same.</head>
               <p>WHereas divers, and sundry Coyns of Gold, and Silver of other Realms, not being the proper Coyn of this Realm of <hi>Ireland,</hi> yet by the sufferance and consent of our Soveraign Lord the King are Currant in payment within this Realm, many Ill-disposed persons, for their own Corrupt Lucre and Advantage, have for these many years last past, and especially now of late brought into this Realm from the parts beyond the Seas great quantities of Forged and Counterfeit mony like to the said Coyn of other Foraign Realms, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have Counterfeited within this Realm, such For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Coyn made by the Kings Sufferance and Consent Currant here, and Wash, File, Clip, and Lighten the same, and have uttered the same here, by Merchandizing and otherwise to divers of the Subjects of this Realm to their great deceipt, hurt and damage the said ill disposed persons, believing (and it being doubted by some) that there was not, nor yet is any sufficient Law, or Statute made or provided for the Condigne punishment of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders in that behalf;</p>
               <p>Be it therefore Enacted by the King Our Soveraign Lord, with the Assent of the Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Temporal, and Commons in this present Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament assembled, and by the Authority of the same; And it is hereby Enacted, that if any person or persons
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:190671:24"/> after the 20th day of <hi>August</hi> next coming,<note place="margin">Bringing in Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Coyn of Foreign Realms. or sorging it here</note> shall bring into this Realm, or into any of the Parts thereof, any such false and Counterfeit Coyn being currant within this Realm as is aforesaid, knowing the same Coyn, and money to be false and counterfeit, or shall forge or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit the same within this Realm, or any parts thereof, or File, Clip, Wash, or Lighten the same, to the intent to utter and make payment with the same within this Realm, or in any parts thereof by Merchandizing or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, that all and every such person or persons so of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending as is aforesaid, their Councellors, Procurers, Ayders, &amp; Abetters in that behalf shall be deemed and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged to be Offenders in high Treason &amp; shall suffer after Lawfull Conviction and Attainder thereof such pains of death, loss, &amp; forfeiture of Lands, Goods, and Chattels as other Offenders shall do in cases of High Treason.</p>
               <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that all and every person or persons that shall at any time after the said 20th day of <hi>August,</hi> be Accused or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached of any of the Offences conteined and provided for in this Statute, or of any other Offences concerning the Impairing, Counterfeiting,<note place="margin">The offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to be tryed as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in like cases of Treason.</note> or Forging of any Coyn currant within this Realm, or the Washing, Fileing, Cliping, or the Lightening thereof shall and may be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted, Arraigned, Tryed, Convicted, or Attainted by such like Evidence, and in such Manner and Form as hath been used and accustomed in like Cases of High Treason within this Realm any Statute, Law, Custom, or Vsage to the contrary thereof in any wise Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 13. An Act Concerning Tythes and other Ecclesiastical Duties</head>
               <p>VVHereas Tyths, Oblations, Obventions,<note place="margin">Tyths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ever since the Lateran Council due to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> having cure of Souls, except on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tyths Impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate.</note> Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and other Ecclesiastical duties and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits growing and arising within all and every the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective Parish and Parishes of this Kingdom, (impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Tyths excepted) have by the Law of the Land, and Constitution of Holy Church, ever since the Councel of <hi>Lateran,</hi> been due and payable to the Respective Pastors, Curates, and Vicars of the said respective Parishes, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:190671:25"/> Cure of Souls therein; as a provision and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for them for serving the said Cure, by celebrating Divine Service, Administring of Sacraments, Preaching and Instructing the Parishioners thereof in true Faith, and performing other Pastoral duties belonging to their Functions.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Catholicks impover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ished by maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Priests, and paying Tythes <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Clergy.</note>And Forasmuch as the Roman Catholick Subjects of this Kingdom for some time past have maintained their own Priests, Pastors, Curates, and Vicars, and thereby have been very much Impoverished by being obliged to pay their Tythes, and other Ecclesiastical duties to the Protestant Clergy, who have not laboured in the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of any of the said Spiritual Offices for any of the said Roman Catholicks.</p>
               <p>Be it therefore Enacted, and it is hereby Enacted by Your Most Excellent Majesty, by and with the Advice and Consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal,<note place="margin">That Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks shall pay their tyths <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to their Priests.</note> and the Commons in this present Parliament Assembled, and by the Authority of the same, that your Majesties Roman Catholick Subjects of this Kingdom, shall and may set out, and pay all their Tythes, Oblations, Obventions, and other Ecclesiastical duties (which of right are due and payable) from henceforth to their respective Roman catholick Priests, Pastors, Curates, and Vicars, and to no other person or persons of what Religion or perswasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on soever, Impropriate Tythes excepted, any Law or Custome to the contrary notwithstanding.<note place="margin">That the Clergy may bring Actions for their tyths</note>
               </p>
               <p>Provided always, and it is hereby further Enacted, that all, and every person and persons of the said Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Clergy, who shall be Intituled to any Tythes or Payments in lieu of Tythes by virtue of this Act, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, and their Proctors, and Farmers, shall and may sue for the same, or the value thereof, by Writ, Bill, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, or Action of Debt, or such other Action, for substra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,<note place="margin">Incapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties taken off</note> or not setting forth the said Tythes, in any of your Majesties Courts within this Kingdom, as he or they might have done, for detaining, or not paying of any Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Duty: And shall and may recover their costs in such Suits. And all Incapacities heretofore devised by any Temporal Law, for disabling any of the said Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Clergy from Enjoying any Benefices or Tythes, or making any Collations or Benefices to them Confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red void, are hereby Discharged, and made void, to all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and purposes whatsoever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:190671:25"/>
               <head>CAP. 14. An Act for Regulating Tythes and other Ecclesiastical Duties in the Province of <hi>Ʋlster.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHereas heretofore upon the Plantation of the Province of <hi>Ulster,</hi> and when there were but few Inhabitants, small Tillage and Inconsiderable Stocks of Cattel in the said Province, there were by Act or Acts of State or Council or some other Temporal Act or Ordinance, greater Tythes or Payments in lieu of Tythes and other Ecclesiastical duties and mortuaries imposed upon and made payable by the Inhabitants of the said Prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce then were Imposed upon or payable by the Inhabitants of other parts of this Kingdom adjacent thereunto for support and maintenance of ministers, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats or incumbents and more particularly the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the said Province were to pay in lieu of Tythes, nine pence for every M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lch cow and calf,<note place="margin">The excess of the tyths in Ulster.</note> and for the year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increase of milk, butter, and cheese of such cow, and four pence half penny for every colpagh and strapper, commonly called gawnagh or cow that giveth milk, the second year, and for the yearly increase of milk, butter, and cheese of such cow, and sixpence for every Foale, and where the clear goods of the defunct, all debts being paid did amount to so much as that the widdow and every one of the Orphants have had a cow, or the value thereof in other goods, which cow was generaly to be appraized at fifteen shillings, then if there was a cow or the value left the Minister was to have fifteen shillings for a mortuary, and although the goods of the defunct should not amount to so much as would satisfie the debts, and give the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and Orphants the aforesaid Portion, then the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster was to have out of every Cow, or the value thereof, nine pence; And whereas the said Province is sin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecome well Planted and Inhabited, in so much that there is great plenty of Corn and Cattel therein, and the said for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Imposition of Tyths, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayments, and Ecclesiastical duties is become very burthensom and oppressive to the Inhabitants of the said Province, and the same being on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Temporary provision for the Incumbent untill bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter provision were made for him, which is since effected by great Gleabs and increase of Corn.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:190671:26"/>
               <p>And whereas when Land was kept for pasture, or lay waste or unwelded,<note place="margin">Tythes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> out of waste Land.</note> the Incumbents did exact the tenth part of the yearly value of the Land, or the tenth part of the Money received for Grazing Cattel thereupon, which was a great Exaction, and very oppressive to the Inhabitants of the said Province.</p>
               <p>Be it therefore Enacted by the King's Most Excellent Majesty,<note place="margin">The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed.</note> by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in this present Parliament assembled, and by the Authority of the same, That the said Act of State, or Act of Council, and every other Act and Ordinance, as to so much thereof as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to the setting forth the Tythes, or to the said respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive payments in lieu of Tythes, Ecclesiastical Duties and Mortuaries herein before particularly expressed, be, and are hereby absolutely Repealed, and made Void.</p>
               <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that the respective Inhabitants of the said Province shall from henceforth be liable to pay yearly one penny half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penny in lieu of Tythes for every Milch-Cow and Calf,<note place="margin">New man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished.</note> and for the increase of Milk, Butter and Cheese thereof, and no more, and for every Mare and Fole one penny and no more; and for every Burial there shall be paid to the Minister, or other Incumbent, one shilling and no more, and to the Clerk and Sexton six pence and no more; but for the Calpagh and Strapper, commonly called Gaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagh, or Cow, which gives milk the second year, nothing shall be paid.</p>
               <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that the said exaction of the tenth part of the yearly value of the Land, or the tenth part of the Money received for Grazing Cattel thereupon be absolutely Abolished, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, and made void; and that in lieu thereof, such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons who have no Tillage within the Parish, but keep and fatten Cattel for sale, if the greatest part of such Cattel be not Milch, then the owners of such Cattel ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no Tillage within the same Parish, shall after the sale of every Bullock or Cow so fattened, and not being a Milch-Cow, pay one penny and no more, and for each Milch-cow, such Tythe as before is set forth; but where the greatest part of such cattel are Milch, then such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and persons shall pay as before for such milch-cattel is set forth, and for the other cattel nothing shall be paid.</p>
               <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:190671:26"/> That whosoever shall sue,<note place="margin">Penalty for offending this Act.</note> molest or trouble any of the Inhabitants of the said Province for any greater, or other Tythes, Duties or Mortuaries, or payment in lieu of Tythes, Duties or Mortuaries for, or in respect of any of the matters or things herein before particularly mentioned and expressed, shall forfeit, and pay double costs and damages to the person or persons who shall be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, molested or oppressed thereby. But as to all other Tythes or payments in lieu of Tythes, and other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastical Duties usually paid, or set forth within the said Province, and not herein particularly mentioned to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, changed, or repealed, the same shall be and remain in the same plight and condition, and no other then as they would have been if this Act had never been made.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 15. An Act concerning Appropriate Tythes, and other Duties Payable to Ecclesiastical Dignitaries.</head>
               <p>WHereas by an Act past in this present Session of Parliament, Entituled,<note place="margin">Recital of a former Act.</note>
                  <hi>An Act concerning Tythes and other Ecclesiastical Duties;</hi> It is amongst other things Enacted, that the Roman Catholick Subjects of this Kingdom shall and may for ever pay their respective Tythes (Impropriate Tythes excepted) and their respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Oblations, Obventions, and other their Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Dues and Duties to their respective Roman Catholick Priests, Pastors, Curates and Vicars, to whom also re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy is given by the said Act for recovering the same. And whereas within this Kingdom there are several Appropriate Tythes formerly belonging to Archbishops, Bishops, Deanes Deanes and Chapters, Collegiate Churches, Archdeacons, Prebends, and other Ecclesiastical Dignitaries.</p>
               <p>And whereas a doubt did arise whether the Roman Catholicks, who are to pay such Appropriate Tythes,<note place="margin">Doubts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise on the former Act</note> are by the said Act to pay the same to their respective Roman Catholick Priests, Pastors, Curates and Vicars, who are Incumbents within the respective Parishes where such Appropriate Tythes are due, or to the respective Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick Dignitaries within such Parishes or pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where such Tythes are payable.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:190671:27"/>
               <p>Be it declared and Enacted, And it is hereby declared and Enacted by the Kings most Excellent Majesty, by the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal and Commons in this present Parliament assembled and by Authority of the same,<note place="margin">Resolution of doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> That the Roman Catholicks of this Kingdom, who are to pay any such appropriate Tythes, shall from time to time, and at all times hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for ever pay the same to the respective Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Arch-bishops Bishops Deans,<note place="margin">who shall have the appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Tyths.</note> Deans and Chapters, Collegiate Churches Arch-deacons, Prebends or other Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick Dignitaries that are or shall be Roman Catholick Dignitaries within the Parishes or Places where such Tythes are or shall be Payable in such manner as the same w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re formerly paid, since the Reformation to the respective Protestant Arch-bishops,<note place="margin">Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> remedy as by the former act</note> Bishops, Deans, Deans and Chapters Collegiate Churches, Arch-deacons, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends, or other Ecclesiastical Protestant Dignitaries of such Parishes or Places, and that the said respective Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Chatholick Arch-bishops, Bishops, Deans, Deanes, and Chapters, Collegiate Churches, Arch-deacons, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends, and other Roman Catholick Dignitaries, shall have the same, or the like remedy for the Respective Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of such appropriate Tythes, as the said Respective Roman Catholick Priests, Pastors, Curats and Viccars, have; or shall have for the Recovery of the Tythes paya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to them Respectively by vertue of the said former Act, any thing in the said former Act, to the Contrary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding.<note place="margin">doubt as to what person shall be deemed within the Act.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And whereas it may be a doubt who shall be deemed, taken or reputed to be Roman Catholick Arch-bishops, Bishops, Deanes, Arch-deacons, or other Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Dignitaries Priests, Pastors, Curates, and Vicars, within the meaning of this, or the said former Act.<note place="margin">Resolution of that doubt.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Be it hereby Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that such Roman Catholick Arch-bishops, Bishops, and Deans,<note place="margin">Dignitaries must have C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tificat under pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy signet.</note> now in being as his Majesty by any Instrument under his Privy signet and signe manual, shall signifie to be Roman Catholick Arch-bishops, or Bishops, of any Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocess, or Deans of such Places or Churches within this Realm,<note place="margin">Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops and Bishops to be by the nominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentation of the king.</note> shall be reputed taken and deemed, the respective Roman Catholick Arch-bishops and Bishops of such Diocess and Deanes of such Places within this Realm, and that such person and persons as hereafter shall be Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick Arch-bishops, or Bishops, of any Diocess
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:190671:27"/> within this Kingdom or Deane of any Place or Church shall be such, and no other as shall be respectively ordained Arch-bishops or Bishops, of such Diocess, or Deanes of such places or Churches by the nomination or presentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Majesty his Heirs and Successors, and that such shall be deemed Roman Catholick Arch-deacons Prebends, or other Roman Catholick Dignitaries,<note place="margin">other dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitaries Priests and Pastors how to be admitted</note> and such shall be deemed Roman Catholick Priests, Pastors, Curates, and Vicars as have been or shall be allowed and approved of by the Roman Catholick Arch-bishops of the Diocess where he or they did or shall officiate, or by the Roman Catholick Bishops of the Diocess, where he or they did or shall Officiate, or where he or they Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectively shall be approved off, or allowed by the Roman Catholick Metropolitan of the Province where such Diocess doth lye, in case there was, or there is, or there shall be no Catholick Bishop, in being of such Diocess at the time of such allowance or approbation.</p>
               <p>And be it further Enacted that the Kings Majesty his Heires and Successors,<note place="margin">The King and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons shall have their presentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> and all such as are or shall be Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick Arch-bishops, Bishops, or other Roman Cath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lick Dignitaries within this Kingdom, and their Successors, and all Roman catholick Lords, Knights, Gentlemen or others, and their Heires and Assignes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectively who have or shall have any advowson, Collati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Right of Presentation, Nomination, or collation to any benefice within this Realm shall for ever hereafter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vacancie of any such benefice have full power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to present or collate a fit person to be the Roman catholick Dignitary, curate, vicar or pastor, of such be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice in such manner and form as they respectively or any of their Predecessors or Ancestors did or could have Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully don.</p>
               <p>And be it further Enacted that so much of any Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes as tends to disable or Incapacitate any of the said Roman catholick Arch-bishops, Bishops, Deanes,<note place="margin">all Incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities <hi>&amp;c.</hi> taken of.</note> Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, Arch-deacons Prebends or any other Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick dignitaries, Priests, Pastors or Vicars of the Roman Catholick Church, from Receiving, Having, Holding, or Enjoying any of the said Ecclesiastical dignities or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings in manner aforsaid, be and is hereby Repealed and made Void.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:190671:28"/>
               <head>CAP. 16. An Act for Repealing the Act for Real Union and Divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Parishes, and concerning Churches, Free-schooles, and Exchanges.</head>
               <p>VVHereas by a Statute made in this Kingdom in the Reign of his la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Majesty King <hi>Charles</hi> the second of Blessed Memory, Entituled an Act for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Vnion, and Division of Parishes, and concerning Churches, Free schooles, and Exchanges; there were cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n Rules Orders and Methods devised whereby to V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te Parishes, and to divide them, and to make Exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the premisses or any part thereof, and to remove Churches from one place to another, and to remove Free schooles from one Town to another, and to divide the possession of any one of the said Schooles into two or more and to Exchange whole Gleabes, or any part of them proportionably, with Bishops Lands of the like value or with so much Temporal Land, and to disappropriate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, and to unite a presentative Church, having Actual cure of Souls to a dignity without cure and to disappro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate any Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tories belonging to any Cathedral Church, and to divide patronages by turns betwixt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, as by the said Statute may more at large appear.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of the former Act</note>And whereas by vertue, or under colour of the said Act, divers Parishes whereof each Parish in times past was sufficient to maintain a Priest, have been united and consolidated together, and by such meanes divers Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters in divers parts of this Kingdom, have had and yet have to each of them, four o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> five or more Parishes for the mainten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce of themselves Respectively, and of their wifes and Families, whereby the good wholsome Laws of this Kingdom against plurality of Benefices have been evad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And whereas by division of Parishes and Livings, and by Exchanges, and other alterations made and done by vertue of the said Act, much confusion and inconvenience hath been Introduced, which for the future are unfit to be continued.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The former Act repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note>Be it therefore Enacted by the Kings most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in this present Parliament assembled, and by authority of the same, That the said Statute, and all and every Vnion, Division, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:190671:28"/> alteration and other matter executed, made or done, pursuant thereunto, or under colour thereof, be and are hereby Repealed and made void.<note place="margin">Provision for Lessees</note>
               </p>
               <p>Provided always and it is hereby Enacted that all Lessees who came into any Lands, Tenements, or Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments by vertue of any Lease or Leases made by any Incumbents under the said Act, shall stand good and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual, but the Rent and Reversion thereof, to goe and Rema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n to such persons to whom the same ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long by the Repeal of the said Act.</p>
               <p>And be it further Enacted that any Patron or Patrons to whom any Advowson or Patronage would have come o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> belonged in case the said Act, were not made,<note place="margin">Patrons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Lapps</note> and whose Rights were barred, disturbed or discontinued thereby, shall not be any way barred or prejudiced, by reason of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Lapps or Latches suffered or supposed to be suffered, since the passing of the said Act, nor shall be deemed to be turned out of Possession by reason of any presentation Admission, Institution, or Induction made Executed or done by reason of the said Act.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 17. An Act for the Relief and Release of <hi>poore</hi> distressed priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for <hi>Debt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOrasmuch as very many persons now detayned in Person, are miserably Impoverished, either by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the present unhappy times, their own misfortunes or otherwise so that they are totally disabled to give any satisfaction to their Creditors, and so becom without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to any, a charge and burthen to the Kingdom, and by Noisomness Inseperably Incident to extream Poverty, may becom the Occasion of Pestilence or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious diseases, to the great prejudice of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>Be it therefore Enacted by the Kings most Excellent Majesty,<note place="margin">persons in Prison 17th <hi>June</hi> 1689. for debt or damages</note> by and with the Consent and Advice of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this present Parliament Assembled, and by the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the same that all persons being in prison upon the 17th day of <hi>June</hi> 1689. for debt or damages, or for, or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Action or Actions, or upon any mean process for debt account or trespass upon the case, which Actions
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:190671:29"/> by prosecution of Law, may be Iudgments for debt or damages, or who have Iudgments entred upon Record against them, or are charged in Execution or Imprisoned upon Attachment for debt, or upon Outlawries before or after Iudgment for debts or upon any other Process whatsoever, Issuing out of any Court of Law or Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for the cause of Debt, or Damages, or Costs only, who shall take the Oath in this present Act mentioned, shall and may be released and discharged from their Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonment in such manner as by this Act is directed.</p>
               <p>And all Iustices of the Peace, within their several Counties and Divisions in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">How Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s of peace shall dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners</note> are hereby authorized and impowered, to put in Execution all such power, directions, and authority, for the full release and discharge of such persons as are in prison on the said 17th day of <hi>June</hi> as aforesaid, and that by Warrant un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Hand and Seal to require the sherriff, Goaler, or Keeper of any Prison within his respective Iurisdiction, to bring without delay, the body of any person being in prison for debt on the said 17th day of <hi>June</hi> as aforesaid, or damages, or for the reasons before-mentioned, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioning such Iustice (to be discharged) to some conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent place within the distance of one mile from the said pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and shall certify the cause and causes of their Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonment before the same Iustice; which Warrant every such sheriff, Goaler, and Keeper is hereby commanded to obey; and in case such prisoners comming before such Iustice shall take an Oath to this Effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Viz. I. A. B.</hi> do upon my corporal Oath solemnly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess and declare before Almighty God that I have not any Estate real or personal in possession,<note place="margin">Oath by prisoner of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty.</note> reversion, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of the value of five pounds in the whole, or suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to pay the debt or damages, for which I am Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prison'd, and that I have not directly or indirectly sold, leased, or otherwise conveyed disposed of, or intrusted all, or any part of my Estate, thereby to secure the same, to receive, or expect any profit or advantage thereof, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud, or deceive any Creditor or Creditors whatsoever to whom I stand indebted.</p>
               <p>Then after the taking of such Oath, the said Iustice shall Remand the said prisoner to Prison, and shall give a Certificate thereof in writing under his Hand and Seal,<note place="margin">Creditor to be sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned.</note> to the same prisoner, to be served upon such person or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, his, or her Executors, or Administrators, or to be left at the place of the usual abode of such person or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:190671:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>